<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Heavens treasvry opened in a fruitfull exposition of the Lord's Prayer together with the principal grounds of Christian religion briefly unfolded / by Tho. Hooker.</title>
            <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 133 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44351</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32035</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12298257</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12298257</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59096</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44351)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59096)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1505:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Heavens treasvry opened in a fruitfull exposition of the Lord's Prayer together with the principal grounds of Christian religion briefly unfolded / by Tho. Hooker.</title>
                  <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>264 p. in various pagings.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Dawlman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Part II, "An exposition of the principles of religion" has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Page 51-54 of Part II is repeated between page 196-197 of part I.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59096:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HEAVENS TREASVRY Opened In a Fruitfull Expoſition of the Lords Prayer. <hi>Together with</hi> The principall Grounds OF <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> briefly unfolded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THO. HOOKER.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Great is the Myſtery of godlineſſe.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 3.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Dawlman.</hi> 1645.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59096:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:59096:2"/>
                  <head>HEAVENS TREASVRY OPENED, In a fruitfull expoſition of the Lords Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the prayer are three things ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The preface, <hi>Our Father.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The prayer it ſelfe, divided into ſix petitions.</item>
                     <item>3. The concluſion of Faith in the word <hi>Amen,</hi> the ſoule goes up to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and followes the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59096:3"/>
                        <hi>Hallowed bee thy Name,</hi> let it bee Lord as thou maiſt have glory; looke as a man that darts an arrow, hee puts the utmoſt of his ſtrength to it, ſo the word <hi>Amen</hi> ſpeeds all the reſt, and brings a good iſſue to the ſoule by all.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Firſt, For the preface, and there wee muſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in generall 2. things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The ſence and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words.</item>
                     <item>2. What ground of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement it affords us to ſeeke God.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. And firſt obſerve the partie ſought to, he is our <hi>Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The excellency of him, <hi>which art in Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59096:3"/>
                  <p n="3">3. The intereſt we have in him: he is <hi>our</hi> Father.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why, or in what ſence, is God called a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Hee is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Chriſt by eternall generation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Hee is the father of men two wayes.
<list>
                        <item>1. By <hi>creation.</hi> So the Scripture runnes <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.6. the Angels are called <hi>the Sons of God,</hi> becauſe they were created by God, hee is a Father thus to the Juſt and the unjuſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 14. <hi>I am wonderfully made,</hi> ſaith the text.</item>
                        <item>2. By <hi>adoption</hi> &amp; grace, in that, hee doth freely take us to bee his ſons in Chriſt, hee puts us into
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59096:4"/>the right of his children, as a man puts a ſtranger into the right of his ſon: and thus God is a Father to his choſen onely that looke what Chriſt hath, they have, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>If Sons, then Heires,</hi> and Gods choſen children: both theſe wayes God is our Father.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Doe we onely pray to the Father in that wee ſay <hi>our Father?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: we pray not to the Father onely, but wee pray to the whole Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wee make mention of the Father onely: yet we muſt direct our prayers to one God in three Perſons in that Godhead; howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wee mention not all,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59096:4"/>yet wee direct to all, all our petitions; the reaſon is this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rea.</hi> Becauſe otherwiſe wee ſhould have made an Idoll of God, I ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving but of one perſon we make an I doll of God, and call not on him as hee is.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How may wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend of God aright in prayer?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus: as God hath revealed himſelfe in his word, ſo wee apprehend him, not putting any I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage at all upon him: as Inſtance thus two wayes.
<list>
                        <item>1. Hee that creates all, governes all, knowes all, ſees all, by whom I live, moove and have my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59096:5"/>to that God I pray. The Scripture hath revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God thus, that he fills heaven and earth, &amp;c. to that God then that is thus infinite, to him I call now, not to a blinde Image, but to an all-ſeeing God I come.</item>
                        <item>2. Inſtance thus. Looke abroad into the creatures, and in all you ſhall ſee a power and a goodneſſe: now from whence came this power? The power of beaſts, came not from the power of trees, and the like: but ther was a firſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, which gave al power to the creatures; the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour is infinitely more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull the the creatures. There is goodneſſe alſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59096:5"/>in the creatures: but all that came from the firſt goodneſſe that let out it ſelfe. Now that which let forth it ſelfe to the creature is in the Creator infinitely above the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that is the Lord: thus you muſt quit your ſelves of an Image; he that gives all is above all; God gives all, therefore is above all, and to that God I put up my petition.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doe wee not mention the <hi>Son</hi> and the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> as well as the <hi>Father?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the Father is the firſt perſon in the Trinity, and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine from whence all good flowes; The <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59096:6"/>works of himſelfe, the <hi>Sonne</hi> of him, the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt</hi> from them both; therefore we mention him onely, though wee may mention the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How doth this word <hi>Father</hi> help a man to call on God by prayer?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When we conceive of God as a Father, it puts us in mind of his mercy, that hee will pity us; as a Father will eaſily bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to his ſonne and will ſpare him, though he be a prodigall, yet his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will paſſe by all. So I pray to a father: did I pray to a <hi>Iudge,</hi> that would condemne me, or an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that would not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto mee, little
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59096:6"/>hope had I to ſpeed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I wronged him,<note place="margin">Luke 15.</note> 
                     <hi>yet I will ariſe and goe to him,</hi> for,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note> 
                     <hi>As a father pittieth his ſonne, ſo God pittieth them that feare him.</hi> Hee is my child ſaith God, though ſtubborne, and I muſt looke to him. When a mans rebellions witnes againſt him, and Sathan vexeth him, and ſaith, what? thou think to have mercy, and art ſo vilde? True, ſaith the ſoule, I am naught, but I goe to a <hi>Father:</hi> if a child doe but aime at a thing, the father accepts; if hee ſpeake but halfe a ſentence, the father interprets it: ſo this is the great encouragement of the faithful, to go to God,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59096:7"/>that notwithſtanding ſo many failings, and though he be ſo dead and ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, yet a father beares al; The Lord interprets all, though but broken ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, yet God accepts and regards all, wee have a father to goe to, that is willing to paſſe by many failings.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As we have a ground of pitty; if it be but a ſigh, hee receives it, ſo this may perſwade us of the willingneſſe of God, to help us. If a man were to goe to him that is hard hearted, little hope had hee to ſpeed: wee ſay hee is a cruell man, we had as good pull water out of a flint, &amp;c. a child will not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59096:7"/>beg of a ſtranger, but goe to his father. So we pray to <hi>our Father</hi> that is more willing to heare and grant then we are to aske. <hi>I will goe to my Father,</hi> ſaith the prodigall, as who ſhould ſay, I am unworthy, yet I goe to a father; nay the Lord heares before wee call, he prepares the heart to call, and anſweres what it craves when they aske. The father puts into the childes mouth what it ſhall ſay, and then hee will give what it craves; ſo God would have us ſeeke for abundance of mercie; <hi>open thy mouth:</hi> God would faine give, but none will crave; it is God that muſt give a heart to crave, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59096:8"/>this is got by prayer. As water put into a pump will bring forth much water, ſo pray that you may pray, if your father know what to give you, how much more can your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father give you an heart? Nothing ſhall bee wanting to them that goe to God as a Father, God bowes his eare to the prayer of his people, hee condeſcends to our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We are here to take notice of Gods Fatherly <hi>providence,</hi> to provide what may bee ſutable to our occaſions; God hath all in ſtore; <hi>all the beaſts of the field are mine,</hi> hee is the God of all comfort;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59096:8"/>hee provideth for the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and cauſeth the Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the field to grow: if God care for theſe, how much more for you?<note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>hath the Lord a care for oxen?</hi> hee that feedeth ravens &amp; clotheth lilies, will much more provide for his Saints. Who then would not have ſuch a guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an? as the father pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for the ſon, ſo God layes up for all his: let us walke then in his wayes, and commit our ſelves to his care, for all things.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. This muſt teach us an awfulneſſe to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, whatawe ſhould bee in our hearts, that come before an <hi>heavenly</hi> Father?</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59096:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That is the terme of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and conſiſts in two things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The ſence of the words.</item>
                     <item>2. The motives.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>For the ſence of the words, three things are implied.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. A proprietie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt wee have in <hi>ſpeciall,</hi> not as one friend to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or one neighbour to another, or the like, but he is <hi>our Father,</hi> as we ſay, it <hi>our</hi> land, &amp;c. So when we ſay <hi>our Father,</hi> we imply aſpeciall claime to God; all that compaſſion and mercy in God is mine, as <hi>Nabal</hi> ſaid, <hi>it is my meate,</hi> the word <hi>my,</hi> implies a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59096:9"/>poſſeſsion, like the gods of the heathens; and as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith: <hi>My Redeemer liveth. Deut.</hi> 32.31. <hi>their rocke, is not</hi> as <hi>our</hi> rocke.</item>
                     <item>2. This laying claime to God implies a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to all the houſhold of God; as the Sunne is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans, ſo God is every mans that is faithfull.</item>
                     <item>3. It notes a bond of ſociety between the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full children of the ſame father: this is the meaning of the word, <hi>our,</hi> as the members agree with the head, ſo they are help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; ſo is God helpfull to all his faithfull ones.<note place="margin">Motives <hi>3.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Now the motives wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſoule may bee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to call on God, are three.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59096:10"/>
                  <p n="1">1. A chearefull <hi>readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> to repaire, unto the Lord, and why? we have an intereſt in him, hee is <hi>our</hi> father; the intereſt a childe hath in his father ſtirs him to come readily to his father, hee craves not of a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger as 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 4.19. When the child cryed, they bad carry him to his mother; if any thing befalls the child, he ſaith, I will tell my father, and complaine to my father; and the like. So aske the child, who will provide for him? he ſaith, my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo it is here with our God. There is a freſh &amp; living way that is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous eaſy and open, <hi>Whoſoever ſeekes ſhall find,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59096:10"/>whoſoever knocks it ſhall be opened unto him:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what ever our injury bee, wee ſhould not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine to the world, but poure forth your prayers to our <hi>Father,</hi> who will bee ſure to heare us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As there ſhould be a cheary readines, to come to the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſo there ſhould bee a ſpirituall <hi>boldneſſe,</hi> to challenge what may be needfull at his hands. Among ſtrangers wee are ſtrange, but among friends wee are bold, wee have a right and title to theſe things, and wee may bee bold with our owne. Thus <hi>David</hi> challengeth God, <hi>as thou art faithfull,</hi> deliver mee, <hi>I am thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59096:11"/>If a ſervant want food or rayment, he goes to his maſter, ſo ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> I am <hi>thy ſervant,</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>give mee underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I may live:</hi> when they bragged of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Apollos,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>all is yours.</hi> This ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our hearts; let us claime our portion, hee is our father, and will give it us.</p>
                  <p>Therefore be humbled in regard of your weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and unworthineſſe, but confident in regard of his mercy, walke cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in regard of the Lord, in every condition. If I ſhould ſee the child doubt of my readineſſe, I ſhould much wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der. <hi>Care
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59096:11"/>not, ſaith Chriſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> It is your owne; hee is our Father, and all that is in him is ours.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This ſtirres up our hearts to have a fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeling of our brethrens miſery, in our prayers: therefore God cuts off all encroaching of our ſelves, <hi>Our:</hi> as if hee ſhould ſay. Is there never a <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in priſon? Never a <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lyons den? re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member &amp; pray for them: if one ſuffer, all ſuffers: wee are reall members of one body: wee ſhould mourne with them that mourne, and weep with them that weep: it is ſaid <hi>Iſay</hi> 58. <hi>Put up a prayer for the remnant.</hi> Oh that wee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59096:12"/>had a fellowfeeling of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers troubles! <hi>Paul</hi> begs <hi>the Epheſians to pray for me alſo,</hi> and hee entreates the <hi>Romans</hi> to wreſtle for him by prayer to God.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.30.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which art in heaven, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here 1. Wee are to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the ſenſe of the word <hi>heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The motives to move the heart thereto.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Whether is God more in heaven then in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other place?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: God in regard of his eſſence is in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces alike, hee is wholly every where. The God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head is altogether indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, Things of quantity fill a roome, but God is euery way indiviſible; as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59096:12"/>hee is unchangeable, ſo is hee a ſimple being.<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.8.</note> 
                     <hi>If I goe to hell, thou art there:</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> God is in the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner every where. If God bee immenſible, then all of him is every where; but it is ſo, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee is altogether in every place: all creatures have their being from God, hee is in them and beyond them, hee is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded <hi>out</hi> of no place, included <hi>in</hi> no place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q</hi> If all of God bee in every place, why then is hee ſaid to bee <hi>in heaven</hi> onely?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe God would manifeſt the glory of his power more in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then in earth, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59096:13"/>we ſee him not here. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. <hi>We grope after him indeed:</hi> but you know the royalty of a King ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares moſt in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo the excellency of God appeares moſt in heaven.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There are three hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; The heavens where the birds are, the heaven where the ſtars are, and the higheſt heaven.</p>
                  <p>Now the third heaven is meant here, for God hath reſerved this place as the chaire of ſtate for himſelfe: <hi>the heavens</hi> ſaith <hi>David, are the Lords:</hi> no uncleane thing can come there. The Angells ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon the earth, and all the viſible heavens are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59096:13"/>defiled: by man, the Sunne is abuſed, the aire polluted; all theſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that ſerve man, are by man defiled, but the higheſt heaven was never defiled, becauſe it is the chamber of God, who leaſeth out theſe to man. This is the ſpeciall reaſon why God is ſaid to bee <hi>in heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What motives have wee to prepare our hearts <hi>to prayer,</hi> which is the ſcope of the preface?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are ſpecially three.</p>
                  <p>It teacheth us to take notice of the purity of God,<note place="margin">Motives. <hi>1.</hi> to prepare the heart to prayer.</note> what ought to bee the frame of our ſpirits, when wee appeare before
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59096:14"/>him; hee cannot abide ſluggiſh prayers from an impure heart; heavenly diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s beſt ſuite with Gods holineſſe, the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of our affections ought to anſwer Gods purity, Kings (we know) as they will be entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo their entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be that which ſuites to their greatneſſe: God is in heaven beyond all corruption, therefore if wee approach neere God, we ſhould anſwer to his purity with hearts pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; that our ſpirits may be in heaven, becauſe he is there, to whom we pray. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Curſed bee the deceiver that hath a male in his flocke, and offers
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59096:14"/>a corrupt thing.</hi> Our <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> is our ſervice, and <hi>prayer</hi> is one of the chiefe. The God of heaven is a pure God, then curſed be the man that hath a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge love and the like, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth God with rubbiſh. <hi>Curſed be that man:</hi> the pure God of heaven will not looke on ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure performances: God is holy, therefore the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ought to be ſo. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men are to ſit before Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they are to fit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves accordingly, ſo it is here.</p>
                  <p>Let us then thinke it an indignity to God to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare with a ſlovenly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition before him: hee that is to performe a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59096:15"/>duty to a Prince, will lay aſide all other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, ſo as he ſaid in an other caſe well, lie by all, ly by world, let me now have heavenly joy, for I am come before an <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is a ground of comfort that our ſpirits may bee cheared: ſince God is in heaven, hee is able to effect what ever our hearts deſire; To be in heaven argueth Majeſtie; now wee doe not pray to an earthly parent who is liable to corruption, but to an heavenly Father, who can doe what hee will; he that is in an high place hath the vantage, ſo our heavenly Father
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59096:15"/>hath the vantage of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, therefore what we crave is done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, our God is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and can doe what he will.</p>
                  <p>Vileneſſe ever accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panieth earthly things, but our Father is <hi>in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> Therefore <hi>Nehemiah</hi> made his prayer to the <hi>God of heaven.</hi> The King could not help the <hi>woman,</hi> but our father is not as an earthly father, wee have but earthly oppoſition here; but our father is in heaven, who can over power all wrongs done to his children and turne them to their good.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This ſhewes wee ſhould with trembling ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59096:16"/>to his preſence: the God of heaven is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull, wee are creeping wormes; &amp; dare we come careleſly to ſuch a <hi>Father? our Father</hi> implies a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe; <hi>in heaven</hi> implies an awfulneſſe; the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines moove, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells ſhake at the preſence of God. Yea the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Angells quake before him: how dare wee then approach his preſence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely, leſt wee have no anſwer? to turne the eye one way and the head another, wee diſlike it in a child: ſuffer not then your minds to wander: how dare you preſſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily into the preſence of God, whereas the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59096:16"/>cover their faces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him? Let the feare of the Almighty fall upon us, God is in heaven, let our hearts bee reverently affected in all our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches neere him.</p>
                  <p>Thus much for the preface; now wee come to the petitions which are ſix, the Lord condeſcends to our weakeneſſe and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe, &amp; therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trives them into a narrow ſcantling: three petitions there are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Gods <hi>Name, Kingdome</hi> and <hi>Wil,</hi> and three concerning our ſelves, things of this life, and things of grace, which are <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> and <hi>Sanctification.</hi> In all obſerve,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59096:17"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. The <hi>meaning</hi> of the petition.</item>
                        <item>2. The <hi>carriage of the heart</hi> in the preſſing of it.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hallowed bee thy name,</hi> in this obſerve 2. things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. What is here ment by <hi>Name?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. What it is to <hi>hallow</hi> this name.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is here meant by <hi>Name,</hi> or what is the Name of God?</p>
                  <p>I anſwer by <hi>Name</hi> is ment, what ever God is made knowne to us by; this is his Name: as a man is knowne by his name, ſo the Lord reveales him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by his Name, to his children: now this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in two things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. All the glorious attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59096:17"/>of God, as <hi>Powerful, Pure, Wiſe, Infinite,</hi> theſe are the <hi>Names</hi> of God.</item>
                     <item>2. All the ordinances of God, the graces of his Saints, and the providence of God, in the creature, (are not the thing it ſelfe, but) there is a declaration of God in theſe, the <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is not the name of God, but <hi>God working</hi> by the creature; <hi>grace</hi> is not ſo much, as the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God in that grace.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do you meane by <hi>hallowed?</hi> can you make God holier then hee is, or adde any thing to God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: we cannot adde anything to him that gave us all things.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:59096:18"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How then doe wee <hi>hallow</hi> Gods name?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When wee make <hi>Gods Name</hi> to bee diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered as a holy thing, the expreſſing of this is that we would.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhall wee doe that?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> There was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation in heaven, how that the Godhead might bee manifeſt, might bee obſerved, elſe were there none to apprehend it: I wil ſaith God, have my at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes expreſſed, Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God would have a world wherein his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhould bee diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. Exod. 33. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſee my face, but my back parts ſhalt thou ſee;</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:59096:18"/>as it is with a torch, carry it from one place to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it will leave a glimpſe behind, ſo it is in the ſurpaſſing beauty of God, hee leaves ſome beames behind him, that wee may ſay, <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>holineſſe</hi> it ſelfe have beene here; we are ſaid then to <hi>hallow</hi> his name when as wee make this appeare, when wee deale with Gods name as with a holy thing, and that appeares in three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the excellency of him, wee ought daily to take notice of the beauty and glory of God: men of place think themſelves
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59096:19"/>abuſed if we paſſe by, and doe not reverence them: ſo when we come to deale with Gods ordinances, doe you know what you doe? Gods Name is there, therefore ponder your paths.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As wee ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the worth of it, ſo we ſhould labour to preſerve it: upon things of great waight and worth what a price doe wee ſet, and how tenderly doe we looke to them, that there bee no blemiſh caſt upon them? So ſhould we doe with the name of God, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.10. Goe to the Iles of <hi>Chittim,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they caſt the commandements of God behind their backs,</hi> the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59096:19"/>heathen ſaith God, would not doe ſo, They kiſſed the threſhold where <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> was; ſo let us deale with <hi>Gods Name,</hi> let no blemiſh betide it, but deale with it, as with a holy thing: the leaſt ſtaine of ſinfull diſtemper, doth not become the name of God: you reſpect holy things, ſo doe this.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As wee ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge its worth, ſo labour to ſet it out that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may ſee it as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall be offered. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any honour may come to him thereby, expreſſe the beauty of the vertues of God that they may bee obſerved; holy things are not to be kept ſecret when
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59096:20"/>opportunity ſerves; <hi>Let your light ſhine</hi> ſaith the text, <hi>that men may ſee the good in you.</hi> What ever we ſee in the <hi>name of God,</hi> as wee ſhould keep it from blemiſh, ſo we ſhould ſet it out in the glory of it; A man muſt hold out the light of the goſpell, not <hi>hide it under a buſhell.</hi> The coyne that is currant men ſhew openly: doe not ſhew <hi>your ſelves</hi> (for that is not herein intended) but as much of God as wee can demonſtrate, that men may ſay, the Lord hath been here indeed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How doth the heart behave it ſelfe in the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of this petition?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This behaviour of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59096:20"/>the ſoule doth mainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in two things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It heartily deſires in all things it ſhall doe, that it may lift up the glory of God; now this wee doe when in all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there is a diſpoſition for the furtherance of Gods praiſe; All our life ſhould be like a lanterne to convey light to others; the heart ſhould deſire that in all things Gods glory may be furthered, that we may doe nothing but we may advance Gods glory by it: ſilver &amp; gold is fit to ſtamp the Kings I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage upon, ſo a mans pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe ſhould be good met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to imprint Gods glory upon, not as painted win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59096:21"/>to hinder,<note place="margin">Acts.</note> but to rebound the light, <hi>Herod</hi> did not give God glory, hee tooke it to himſelfe, and we ſee what enſued.</p>
                  <p>There bee ſome kind of glaſſes will reflect a mans Image: So there ſhould bee a conveighing of glory from our ſelves to God; looke as it is with a ball, the falling of it makes it rebound, ſo it ſhould be with our hearts, they ſhould rebou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Gods glory where it falls upon us: This is a great skill; the ſoule ſhould have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but whereby God might bee honoured; any ſinfull courſe blemiſheth Gods glory, any priding of a mans ſelf no whit fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59096:21"/>Gods glory; a good ſoule deſires God might be acknowledged &amp; glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in all it hath or doth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> When doth the ſoule doe this?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When it labours that in all things ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then humane excellency may appeare; for if any thing of a mans owne bee diſcerned, wee fall ſhort of Gods <hi>Name.</hi> In every actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch ſhould be our diſpoſition, that ſomewhat more may bee ſeene, then a baſe meane ſhadow: there is a skill in <hi>preaching</hi> and <hi>praying,</hi> which ſhould bee more valued then all parts, and gifts whatſoever. If no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing appeare but ſelfe,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59096:22"/>the <hi>Name</hi> of God is depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of what it ſhould have; as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Doe I ſpeake like a man?</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated the ſpirit in him, ſo ſhould wee diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what we do, that God works it in us, that hee might have all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. God who is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all, ſhould have the glory of all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Wee talke of this &amp; that, and ſay, <hi>let God be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified,</hi> but wee doe it not in our life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What bee the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall works of the heart in doing this, that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that God is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all, &amp; we give him the honour is due unto his <hi>Name?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:59096:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The acts of the heart are two, whereby it ſets forth the glory of God. 1. In all ſervices: a man ſhould not bee quiet in his affections &amp; endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours till he come to the higheſt pitch, that is Gods glory: All Actions are in the way one towards another, as a paire of ſtaires, one goes from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other and above the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a man ſhould goe higher and higher til God his glory mounts and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts them all: as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter firſt ſtudies to teach the people that they may be enformed, but why en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed? that they may appeare to bee Chriſts, that Gods grace may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59096:23"/>in their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſoule never reſts till it be here. This ſhould bee our deſire, that in all our actions God may bee diſcovered to bee the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour and to have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ſoule muſt bee ſure not to goe beyond Gods glory, as thus; a Miniſter <hi>preacheth,</hi> that the people may bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and bee honoured as well as God: this is to bee above God; a man <hi>prayes</hi> to honour God, and that it may be known he is a glorious profeſſor, thus a man is above God, as a bird ſteps from one bough to another, till it comes to the higheſt, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59096:23"/>then it flies away, ſo wee ſtep to Gods glory and oft times goe beyond it.</p>
                  <p>Wee would have God glorified to glorifie us it may bee; but this is hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, to have God ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured that wee may bee ſecretly baſe; this is the deepeſt diſhonor to God, and hee will bee revenged of them one day, &amp; pluck his praiſe out of their bowells: the three <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> would not ſtay till the ſtarre ſtood, and then they went no further; ſo where the ſtarre of Gods glory goes let us goe, and not ſtay till we come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and when wee are there goe no further; this
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59096:24"/>is the cariage of the heart, that in life and death God may bee honoured and exalted: looke as it is with a workeman that makes a peece of curious worke, wee doe not give the honour to the toole but to the workeman, ſo God ſhould receive the honour of all and from all.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As a good ſoule makes God diſcovered in himſelfe, ſo hee deſires that God might bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by others: and that appeares in two things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That they might em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the excellency of God, <hi>Let your light ſhine before men,</hi> why ſo? that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59096:24"/>they may ſee your good works that is God in your good works. Doe not thinke that I would have men ſee their owne good parts, gifts and the like, but onely that they may ſee God in them; the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher deſires that the fiſh may ſee the baite, not him; ſo hee that angles for the ſoules of others, doth not deſire that others might ſee him, but the grace of God: An apprentice doth not ſtand in the ſhop to call men to looke on his properneſſe and the like, but to ſell his maſters wares. If we deſire that God may bee exalted, labour not that men may ſee <hi>your good works</hi> ſo
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59096:25"/>much, as God in them; wee ſhould all ſo walke, that others may admire Gods grace in us, wee are GODS workeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</item>
                     <item>2. And therfore ſhould have hearts enlarged to bleſſe God that hee hath been pleaſed to reveale himſelfe ſo ſweetly to us: thus much for the firſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thy Kingdome come.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Petition.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this added immediatly to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall meanes whereby the glory of God is advanced. The firſt was to hallow <hi>Gods Name,</hi> and to that end the Kingdome of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59096:25"/>Chriſt muſt bee ſet up: no naturall man can glorifie God, for ſo long as ſinne and corruption prevailes, wee can never yeeld to him: therefore the rule of Chriſts Spirit muſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it, and by this wee muſt bee ſwayed to the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the ſcope of this petition?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The maine ſcope of it, is thus much, that the government of God by Chriſt, might be ſet up, and prevaile every where: as before Gods Name was higheſt, ſo here the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and governement of Chriſt, is to bee univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall; that is in generall. Now wee come to the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59096:26"/>particulars, and here
<list>
                        <item>1. Conſider the ſence of the words.</item>
                        <item>2. The cariage of the heart, in putting up this petition.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. What is meant by Kingdome.</item>
                     <item>2. What is the coming of this Kingdome.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is meant by <hi>Kingdome?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By <hi>Kingdome</hi> is meant, that rule that Chriſt hath ſet up in the hearts of his (for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, I take it, is not ſo much aymed at, in this place, or that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary providence of God over the creatures: this is ſet forth in the fourth pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, give us, &amp;c.) but it
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59096:26"/>is the rule of Chriſt that is ſet up in his Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How manifold is it?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is that whereby Chriſt by his Spirit and grace in the miniſtery of the word takes place in the hearts of his, and this he doth two wayes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. By overpowering and caſting downe all other things, which are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite thereunto: whatſoever power of ſinne and Sathan are oppoſite unto him.</item>
                     <item>2. He ſets up that frame of ſpirit whereby it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to grace, and this takes place two wayes.
<list>
                           <item>1. By cutting downe &amp; killing of every ſinne.</item>
                           <item>2. The ſoule takes the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59096:27"/>ſtamp of every command of God, and is ruled ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Gods immediate ruling in the hearts of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Saints.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How doth the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> differ?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Here in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of grace, God rules,
<list>
                        <item>1. By his ſpirit,</item>
                        <item>2. By the miniſtery of his word and ordinances, but in heaven he rules immediatly, then no more word &amp; means, but Chriſt fils the ſoule fully, and then he rules gloriouſly when the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding will and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are full of Chriſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59096:27"/>and are fully and wholly ſubject to him, Here in the valley of teares, wee meet with many rubs and oppoſitions, but then Chriſt ſhall ſhine imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately forth, in all his ordinances: wee ſeeke a Chriſt now, but then wee ſhall fully poſſeſſe him: ſo that wee that have the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit have a glimpſe of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, already, therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed ſhould wee bee to bee weary of God: let us bee weary of ſinfulnes &amp; of this wretched world.</item>
                     </list>
It is a heaven to live here with God upon earth, and if it be ſo glorious a thing, to have but a glimpſe of God here, how much more to bee filled with
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59096:28"/>God hereafter in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How is this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> ſaid <hi>to come?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The coming of theſe two Kingdomes implyes three things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That the word may bee revealed in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where it hath not been. That the day ſpring from on high, may viſite them, that ſit in darknes; That the Sunne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, might viſite them that want it; That the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of the Goſpell may be ſet up. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. If any man ſay, hee is in the wilderneſſe, goe not out, for <hi>where the Carkaſſe is, thither will the Eagles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort.</hi> This is the firſt thing,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59096:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>a Kingdome is ſaid to-come when a King rules in a place where hee did not before, ſo it is here, <hi>Let all the people praiſe thee</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> hee deſires not, that ſome tongues onely, but that <hi>all</hi> tongues and languages ſhould doe this.</item>
                     <item>2. Where ever the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell doth ſhine, wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that it ſhould diſcover it ſelfe more fully, and ſpread it ſelfe where ever it comes; wee deſire the Kings governmet ſhould enlarge the Territories more and more. So we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that not onely Chriſt ſhould bee revealed, but that more and more may bee gathered, that God
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59096:29"/>may take in every where, and that every knee may bow to Chriſt, and licke the duſt, that ſo there may be an addition made to the Church, that every man in every kind, God would caſt his skirt over him, that more may bee caught in his net, that the Jew and Gentile may be gathered into one ſheep-fold and have one ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard.</item>
                     <item>3. That the power of it may be more ſettled: as <hi>the houſe of David grew ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er &amp; ſtronger, but the houſe of Saul grew weaker and weaker;</hi> ſo when Chriſt ſets up his candleſticke that the ſeed that is ſowne there may take deep root.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59096:29"/>When a King hath ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Caſtles then he hath his Kingdome. So we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire God may entrench himſelfe and reare caſtles of defence againſt his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies which would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him in us; that hee would ſet up himſelfe ſtrongly, that every trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour might bee cruſht and every baſe luſt ſubdued, that God would ſlay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and none but his lawes might take place in our ſoule. In a word the iſſue returnes to thus much; wee beſeech Chriſt, that his Goſpell may ſpread and be ſtrong, and theſe dayes of ſinne may bee waſted, and that he may come in the clouds. <hi>Rev.</hi>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:59096:30"/>22. and then come Lord Jeſus, come quickly, that he would accompliſh the number of his Elect, and gather thoſe that belong to his glory, that they may be everlaſtingly with him.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the carriage of the ſoule in putting up this petition?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It appeares in three things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The ſoule deſires and labours to bee ſubject to the good pleaſure of the Lord. The heart faith, oh that I might once bee ſo diſpoſed that I might ſubmit to the pleaſure of the Almighty. We deſire that all thoſe things that are ſet up in our hearts,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59096:30"/>which are contrary to the good will of the Lord might bee ſubdued, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.4. <hi>Thou haſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us to keep thy Precepts: o Lord, that my ſoule were ſo affected!</hi> thou haſt enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee to keepe thy Law: oh, that I could doe ſo. The ſpirit ſhould bee as waxe to the ſeale, and inke to the paper, that the ſoule might take the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of every rule that God would ſet up in our hearts: thus the ſoule ſhould bee diſpoſed, and wiſh that the Lord would put this frame into us: <hi>thou haſt ſaid, ſeeke my face:</hi> oh, ſaith the ſoule, <hi>that I could ſeeke thy face,</hi> and echo to it, <hi>behold
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59096:31"/>Lord, thy face doe I ſeeke:</hi> to ſubmit wholy without any contending: not that the Lord ſhould force us, but take up your yoake, put our necke to the yoak: let the word of the Lord beare the ſway: when <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> wanted <hi>wine</hi> and our Saviour checked her, ſhee ſubmitted preſently, not a word more; ſo what the Lord commands us, let us doe without any quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling, let the leaſt inck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the word beare the ſway. When our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſent his diſciples for the <hi>Aſſes colt,</hi> they ſaid, but <hi>happily, the men will not let him goe,</hi> how then? Tell them ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>the Maſter hath
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59096:31"/>need of him, and then they will not deny him:</hi> It is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough, let the Lord but ſpeake and it is done, this the ſoule ſhould labour to attaine unto.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ſoule carries it ſelfe with an inward op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to what ever is oppoſite to the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to the uttermoſt of our power. It is in vaine to ſay, it were well if it were ſo; and I would it were ſo, and yet ſtand ſtill and not to ſet to our hand; but we muſt joine with the Lord, and as hee ſpake of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſh, Curſed be thou, becauſe thou wenteſt not out to help the Lord,</hi> ſo truly the Lord Jeſus is coming to our
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59096:32"/>townes, to our families, therefore we ſhould ſtep out and help the Lord againſt thoſe high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneneſſe</hi> of heart; when a proud heart ſtirres, would wee but cry out, good Lord help downe with that ſtubborne ſpirit of mine, how ſoone would it yeeld! but if you ſay, come pride, and you and I will joyne together, is this calling for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt to come? no, no, you are traitours and conſpirators, and no ſubjects; therefore ſtop your mouthes; this is no ſubmitting, but conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Ieſabel</hi> looked
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59096:32"/>out of the window with <hi>her painted face,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iehu,</hi> who is on my ſide? <hi>fling her out:</hi> ſo ſaith the Lord, will you have pride or mee? If you bee on my ſide, fling downe that proud, untoward heart, which hinders the Lord Jeſus, for taking place in your ſoules: you paint your ſelves in a proud hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; but if you bee on Gods ſide, downe with thoſe painted ſtrumpets. Wee muſt not onely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe great ſinnes, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſinne, wee muſt not ſod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r with any ſecret cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption although it be but the appearance of evill, it we muſt abſteine f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Maſes</hi> ſaid <hi>leave not a hoofe,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59096:33"/>would hee ſtart an haires bredth from Gods commandement, in any particular, but ſubdue all.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Though the ſoule cannot bee as it ſhould, yet it doth deſire the Lord (whether ſinne will or no) to rule us, and lay all flat downe under the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veremnt of Chriſt: when the heart findes a great deale of untowardneſſe &amp; power of ſinne, then it ſaith, Lord thy Kingdome ſhould prevaile, but the ſonnes of <hi>Zerviah</hi> are too ſtrong for mee; therefore take power to thy ſelfe and plucke away what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doth oppoſe thee. It was a good ſpeech of a good Chriſtian, that hee
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59096:33"/>deſired the Lord to rule whether he would or no. Thus the ſoule ſhould be diſpoſed to entreat the Lord that he would break open the doore: when the Lord comes, and we will not open, wee deſire the Lord would come in by a kind of violence, the ſoule intreates the Lord to conquer, to breake in, and make way into the heart, and to take poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion wholly in the ſoule. Now when the ſoule is loath this ſhould bee, it is a wretched ſpirit; when the Lord will ſubdue ſin, and we are loath it ſhould bee ſo, doe wee then pray <hi>Chriſts Kingdome ſhould come?</hi> When wee are not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59096:34"/>able to beare a command of his? no, no, the ſoule will then labour to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ſinne, and pray to the Lord for power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thy will be done in earth as it is in heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the third Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Petition.</hi>
                     </note> and in it are three things obſervable.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The order of the ſame.</item>
                     <item>2. The ſence and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words.</item>
                     <item>3. The frame of the heart in the putting up of this petition.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. For the <hi>order,</hi> the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe the two former petitions, make way for this third, he that glorifies God by all and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59096:34"/>hath his power ſet up in his ſoule, hee onely doth Gods commands; for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally there is no ability in man to doe the will of God, but when the ſpirit works within, then we are able to frame our hearts to Gods will. <hi>David</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man after Gods own heart, was alwayes ready to doe his will: this is the reaſon of the <hi>order,</hi> of the petition: from the ground thereof obſerve two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That he that thinkes out of his owne power to doe Gods wil, it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible hee ſhould doe it: no, hee ſhall never doe it.</item>
                     <item>2. Wee muſt firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Kingdome of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59096:35"/>Chriſt before we can doe his will; Bee under the government of grace, and then thou mayeſt goe on cheerefully, wee faile, if before wee have ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wee would bee doing; firſt, Chriſt muſt doe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible things to the heart before it will yeeld to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; now for the meaning of the words.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the will of God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the purpoſe of the Almighty, touching the accompliſhment of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing; there is nothing done but the Lord doth it: whatſoever is brought to paſſe, that is Gods will in generall. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How many kinds of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59096:35"/>
                     <hi>wills</hi> is there, or how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold is the will of God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is twofold, not in regard of it ſelfe, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of us.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The revealed will of God.</item>
                     <item>2. The ſecret will of God.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="2">2. What is the ſecret will of God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is that ſecret pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe hee hath in himſelfe, before al worlds, and hath not diſcovered it to the creature. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.9. ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made knowne unto us the miſtery of his will according to his good pleaſure, which he hath purpoſed in himſelfe: the Goſpell was hid in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Almighty, not obſerveable by man or any creature under hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59096:36"/>but now it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. Who knowes the mind of God? the deep things of God? none knowes but the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God; and as it is not made knowne, ſo wee have nothing to doe with it in this place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led will of God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the purpoſe of God, which he hath made known to us by his word, and revealed to us in his works.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is this doing of the will of God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It conſiſts in, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies two things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That what ever God makes knowne to bee his will to lay upon us wee
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59096:36"/>ſhould willingly ſubmit &amp; yeeld unto: if God would have me poore, when it is done wee ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proove of the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods will. It is the breach of many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, that when God thwarts our deſire, we are unwilling it ſhould bee done. The <hi>wife</hi> is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content that the husband ſhould die, &amp; the <hi>husband</hi> that the wife ſhould die: never loſt man ſuch a wife as I, this is profeſtly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this petition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I held my tongue and ſaid nothing,</hi> ſaid the Prophet, <hi>will the Lord have it?</hi> then not a word more, his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit yeelds preſently, takes the ſtroake, doth not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59096:37"/>thwart the good will of God; which likewiſe was the practiſe of <hi>David, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Hezechia: It is the Lord, let him doe what hee will.</hi> Nay, our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelfe ſaith, <hi>not my will, but thy will bee done.</hi> This is the folly of our hearts, we take armes againſt Gods will, God would have us to be poore and wee will be rich. This is not to doe the will of God; though God force us to it, yet that is no thanks to us, we ſinne deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratly in our averſeneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The heart is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly content with what God doth, whether loſſe of life, friends, liberty and the like, but there is another
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59096:37"/>will muſt be done beſides: what God reveales to bee a duty muſt be diſcharged by us. If there be a truth to bee made knowne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, wee muſt acquaint our ſelves with the will of the Lord, and with all diligence practiſe it. Make my heart one with thine, that I may ever feare thy Name, let thy will bee mine; oh, ſaith the ſoule, that I might ever feare thy name! this is to doe the will of God.</p>
                  <p>Wee doe not ſay, let it be ſpoken of, and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of by mee, but let it bee done, let it bee accompliſhed fully in me; wee muſt not lift at it, and give GOD good
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59096:38"/>words and talke and leave it undone, but labour to doe it throughly; It is not enough for the child to ſay, I know what my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commands mee, but I will doe what I liſt: ſuch hearts cannot pray to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any thing at the hands of God, now and then to looke at a duty ſaying, I would it were ſo; away with that ſluggiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to wiſh the will of God were done, and yet you will have your owne wils, and runne according to your owne fancies.</p>
                  <p>To this precept it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, that wee ſhould ſet on others to doe Gods pleaſure. In vaine doe we wiſh it to bee done, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59096:38"/>doe not provoke others to doe it; when <hi>Agrippa</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> were grapling together, ſaith <hi>Agrippa,</hi> thou haſt <hi>almoſt perſwaded mee to bee a Chriſtian,</hi> not almoſt, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> but <hi>I would have thee altogether as I am, except theſe bonds;</hi> I would not have thee fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered as I am, but enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged in heart to doe Gods will.</p>
                  <p>Therefore ſaith <hi>Ioſhua, I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord;</hi> he that not only neglects Gods will him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but hinders others, that man doth not pray this petition aright, he that ſaith, <hi>thy will bee done,</hi> and in the meane time withdrawes others by his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59096:39"/>ſecret allurements &amp; ſaith, <hi>what, ſhould I bee ſuch a foole? to bee at other mens bow and becke, to ſit howling in a corner as thou doſt? no, no;</hi> well, bee it knowne unto thee, thou that wilt not doe Gods will here, the Lord will have his wil done on thee one day to thy coſt; hee that will not doe Gods will here, God will ſend him packing to hell hereafter, and there hee will execute his will upon him whether he will or no.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How muſt wee doe the will of God? we doe now and then ſtumble on a duty; and now and then take up a ſervice, but yet wee are now &amp; then pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59096:39"/>and wayward, Is not this enough?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No, no, you muſt <hi>doe it in earth,</hi> as <hi>it is done in heaven,</hi> not now to bee ſome thing, and then to be nothing, now a Saint and then a Divell, but you muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly obey God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q</hi> Can a man doe the will of God on earth as the bleſſed Angells doe it in heaven?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A man cannot doe it in that meaſure the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells doe it, but wee may doe it as they doe, and performe the ſame obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience with them, though not in quantity, yet in quality; a child followes the father though it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not runne ſo faſt as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59096:40"/>a ſcholler may imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the copy and write after it, though not write ſo faſt and well. So the ſervants of the LORD cannot doe the will of God here in that quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity that the <hi>Angells</hi> doe it in heaven, but in quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty like them: let their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience be our patterne, not in the meaſure, but in the manner of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> In what things muſt it bee done? how can we expreſſe any action like theirs?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This reſemblance is in foure particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 They doe it <hi>readily,</hi> they are ready preſt at hand to doe the good wil of the Lord, upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59096:40"/>They are not withdrawing themſelves, but ready upon every oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to doe what the Lord requires <hi>Iob.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job. 1.</note> It is ſaid, that <hi>The Sonnes of God appeared before him;</hi> they are ever in his ſight to give attendance to him, as a handmaid is at the hand of her miſtres. So that of <hi>Iſaiah, They cover their faces before the mercy ſeat,</hi> they cover their faces, <hi>in token of awfulneſſe and reverence,</hi> and cry <hi>holy, holy, holy.</hi> They are ever before him as a dutifull ſervant at his maſters beck and call.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Angells</hi> ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the face of God, hee cannot becken but
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59096:41"/>they are at hand: In this readineſſe of theirs to doe the will of the Lord, wee ſhould imitate them, to be ever prepared to ſerve him, not to have our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſtragling, but with <hi>Abraham, behold thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant is at hand:</hi> thus it ſhould bee with the ſoule: The Lord ſaith, you muſt not have this ſinne and that corruption; we muſt reply, <hi>Thy will bee done Lord,</hi> not as <hi>Moſes</hi> when the Lord comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded him to goe to <hi>Pharoah,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>who am I Lord, ſend another?</hi> no, it ſhould not bee thus with us, wee ſhould be ready at hand: here Lord, <hi>ſpeake, for thy ſervant heareth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:59096:41"/>
                  <p>Goe to <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> ſaith the Lord to <hi>Ananias,</hi> and hee went, for all he had been a perſecutor. <hi>Ionah</hi> will goe to <hi>Tarſhiſh</hi> rather then to <hi>Niniveh.</hi> Wee ſhould not doe thus, but as <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> when hee ſent for <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>we are all here before God,<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> to take notice of whatſoever it ſhall pleaſe him to reveale to us.</hi> Let your lamps bee light and prepared, that whether the bridegroome come at midnight, or at any other time, all may be in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe at a puſh, when hee calls: when the Lord ſaith, here is a ſinne to be ſorrowed for, I ſubmit Lord, ſaith the ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Wee muſt not let God
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59096:42"/>ſtay for us to bee haled to any duty, no, but we muſt attend his will, neither muſt wee ſtand it out, <hi>I will bee wicked, and I will walke in mine own way ſtil,</hi> ſo you may periſh, and for ever bee damned and goe to hell when you have done: this is not to doe the will of God as it is done in heaven.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Angels came before God,</hi> and the text ſaith <hi>the Divell came alſo by force,</hi> full ill againſt his will; ſo wicked men dare not, but they muſt leave ſome ſins, but that is perforce: they are either conſtrained to it by the Lawes of men or by the horrour of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and the like, not
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59096:42"/>with ready and chearefull ſpirits.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Angells doe the will of God <hi>ſpeedily,</hi> they delay not, but are willing and preſſe in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of Gods will, if the Lord doe but becke they are gone. <hi>Iſay</hi> 6. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells are ſaid to have <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers wings,</hi> ſome to cover their faces, in token of humiliation, ſome to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their feet, to ſhew their ſpeed and haſt to performe what God at any time ſhal enjoyne and commaund.</p>
                  <p>This we ſhould as they doe, ſhake off all lingrings of ſpirit, when wee ſee a thing ſhould bee done, and God requires it: na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59096:43"/>wee are marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous lazie in our Chriſtian courſe, and come like a Beare to the ſtake, is this to doe the will of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells doe? No certainly: <hi>David</hi> prayſed the Lord with his beſt abilitie, and ran the wayes of Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, ſo ſhould wee make haſt and delay not.</p>
                  <p>When the Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſha</hi> ſent his ſervant to the <hi>womans ſonne,</hi> hee bad him <hi>ſalute no man,</hi> make no ſtay by the way: this marvellous care ſhould be in us: Pray for our lives, and runne on in a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an courſe for our lives, not to trifle, but to goe with
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59096:43"/>all ſpeed till wee come to our journeyes end, not ſluggiſhly as if a man ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not, whether hee did it or no, If profit or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure would be tampering with us, ſalute them not, wee ſhould take up our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions; if honour and profit would bee hanging about us, fling them off, let us not regard them, but ride poſt haſt.</p>
                  <p>When our Saviour ſent his diſciples out to preach, hee bad them <hi>cary neither ſcrip nor ſtaffe to hinder them in their courſe;</hi> when <hi>Paul</hi> was converted, the text ſaith, <hi>he never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with fleſh and blood,</hi> hee adviſeth not with car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reaſonings, but what
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59096:44"/>God commands hee did; ſo when God calls for du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wee ſhould not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with profit, pleaſure and honours, aske them leave, to take up this duty and that performance, If the holy Apoſtle had done this, it would have hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, but hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted not with fleſh and blood: ſo we ſhould doe ever what God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands: it matters not what men would have of us, but let us have an eye to Gods command.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Angells in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven doe the will of God <hi>faithfully;</hi> that is, they performe the <hi>whole will</hi> of God, they faile not to doe it to an haires bredth:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59096:44"/>hee is a faithfull ſervant that doth his maſters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand fully, ſo ſhould a Saint doe: now faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes appeares in 2. things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Wee muſt doe it all as they doe.</item>
                     <item>2. Wee muſt doe it in the right manner, which God requires.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>This is faithfulneſſe; the Angells doe not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh what meſſage they will, but God ſets it downe, and his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure takes place. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.21. <hi>They fulfill the good pleaſure of the Lord,</hi> they ſtart not at any ſervice, no croſſe: they ſtand not at duty, they doe it, becauſe he commands, ſo it ought to bee with the hearts of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59096:45"/>the people of the Lord, wee muſt not picke and chuſe, do it in an aguiſh fit when wee liſt; It is ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> he did all the will of God.</p>
                  <p>It is ſufficient God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, though it be tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: the Angells care not though all the Divells in hell rage: ſo the Saints of God ſhould doe: be it te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, that skills not, ſo we may finiſh our courſe with comfort; hee doth not picke and chuſe, but feares every finne, and takes up every duty.</p>
                  <p>The text ſaith, <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua</hi> followed God fully in the dayes of <hi>Macaba</hi> and <hi>Meribah,</hi> in the times of trouble: here is an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelike
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59096:45"/>ſpirit, to goe through with the worke. Though father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet they would goe on. The contrary was the finne of <hi>Sardis,</hi> and which God reprooves ſharply, <hi>I have not found thy works full:</hi> it is nothing to do ſome of Gods will, but wee muſt doe it all, or elſe the Lord regards it not. The moſt wicked will do wel ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for their own ends, if they bee pleaſed. That is nothing; thou muſt doe Gods will pleaſed or not pleaſed, or elſe thou haſt a Satanicall ſpirit; not to ſay the dayes are trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but goe through, as the Angells doe.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:59096:46"/>
                  <p>Secondly, the manner; as we muſt doe the <hi>whole</hi> wil of God, ſo we muſt doe it after the right <hi>manner;</hi> not as you will, but as hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> when hee was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to goe offer his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> went early in the morning: if hee had been to offer an oxe it had been nothing: but <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt give his onely Sonne <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the Sonne of the promiſe, to be a ſacrifice.</p>
                  <p>So for us not to bee drunke, and commit out ragious finnes, ſuch as all the world crie out of, thats nothing; but thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret luſts, thy beloved <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaaks,</hi> they muſt bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned.</p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:59096:46"/>
                  <p n="4">4. The Angells doe the will of God <hi>conſtantly:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 18.</note> where they are daily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the face of God, they hold out and perſevere to doe Gods will: this ſhould bee our practiſe: though wee cannot doe it in that manner and ſo much as they, yet endeavour for it, <hi>continue to the death,</hi> ſaith the text, and what then, <hi>I will give thee the crowne of life:</hi> our reward ſhall bee for ever, let our labour bee ſo; a Saint ſhould bee 4. ſquare, the ſame for ever, not to fall backe to be good in good company, with profeſſors profeſſe, and with ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers curſe, with drunkards bee drunkards, and with
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59096:47"/>divells bee divells. The bleſſed Angells doe not thus. The Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends the good ſteward, <hi>Happy ſhall that ſervant bee, whom his Maſter when be comes ſhall find ſo doing,</hi> when the Lord ſhall come and find a Saint perſevere unto the end, hee ſhall be bleſſed indeed. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells will outbid us in the meaſure of performance of Gods will: but yet we ſhould bee <hi>ſpeedy, ready, faithfull, conſtant,</hi> as they are, in uprightnes, though not in that meaſure of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actnes that they doe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the frame of the heart, in the putting up of this petition?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It appeares in two things.</p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:59096:47"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. It is willing to doe it, it ſelfe.</item>
                     <item>2. It is willing and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to help and ſtirre up others to the utmoſt of its power to doe the will of God.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. The ſoule ought to bee forward to know the will of God, and doe it, it ſelfe: and this appeares in foure particulars.</p>
                  <p>1. The heart is willing to doe the will of God, in laying downe <hi>its owne</hi> wil, ſo farre as it may bee an hinderance in doing Gods will; for oftentimes our will and the will of God are contrary. There is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally a refractorie ſtiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that lifts up it ſelfe above the Lord; this muſt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59096:48"/>bee remooved, not my will ſaith our Saviour, but thy will bee done. If our wills and Gods, cannot ſtand together, we muſt lay down ours. But ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we ſay deſperately (as they did) wee will walke in our owne wayes, &amp;c. wee will have a King as other nations, wee will have our baſe luſts, to ſway and rule us; but ſo long as this is in us, we cannot doe the will of the Lord, wee cannot ſerve two maſters, <hi>I came not to doe mine owne will, but my Fathers that ſent mee,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour. It is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with our will and the will of God, as with two buckets, the letting
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59096:48"/>downe of the one is the lifting up of the other, and the lifting up of the other is the letting downe of that; ſo where wee let downe our owne wills we lift up Gods, but where wee lift up our owne wills wee let downe the good will of the Lord. Now the cauſe why wee ſticke in ſervice &amp; cannot come off is, wee would have our pleaſures, we would bee this and that, ſo that the will of God is juſtled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wall and ſhut out of dores: but let this diſtemper bee cruſht, and then the will of God will take place.</p>
                  <p>2. When we have done this, then wee muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59096:49"/>to the Lord to know what his pleaſure is, take his warrant before we ſet upon the worke; a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable attendance on Gods will, ſhould be the root &amp; ſpring of all our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, not to goe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, but to have our ſpirits carried by it. This is a maſter controler that ſwayes and beares all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: tell mee not, I cannot doe it for my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties ſake, &amp;c. But I have no warrant out of GODS will, unleſſe the good will of the Lord goe before me, I dare doe nothing. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.10.11. proving what is acceptable to the Lord. As the Gold-ſmith layeth
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59096:49"/>the gold to the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton, ſo prove your ſelves, ſee what is acceptable to the Lord. In the time of the old Law they put on the linnen <hi>Ephod</hi> and went to enquire of the Lord. Thus <hi>Saul</hi> enquired of the Lord, whether the men of <hi>Kedar</hi> would come up: ſo ſhould wee doe, come to the Lord (that is the touchſtone) and ſee what the Lord would have us to doe, and not goe to a company of carnall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours to conſult with honour, eaſe, wife, family, &amp;c. Whether ſhall I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer (ſaith the ſoule): ſayes honour, if you doe thus, I am laid in the duſt; ſayes eaſe and profit, for my<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59096:50"/>part, if you take this courſe I am utterly undone and loſt: then ſaith the ſouls, if it bee thus I will not doe it, let all ſinke &amp; ſwimme: thus they doe not Gods will but their owne. But they that doe the will of God, let them enquire what his will is; let honor, eaſe, profit, world, and all ſay what it will, they will doe what the Lord will have: wee muſt not maſter conſcience, (It was the ſpeech of a wicked wretch, one of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions being in horrour of conſcience, hee bad him maſter it as hee did, for before that hee could never live quietly; but now hee was not at all
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59096:50"/>troubled with it, maſtering of conſcience in Engliſh, is ſearing of conſcience) but that muſt maſter you and lead you to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of duty.</p>
                  <p>3. When this will of God is revealed, we muſt yeeld unto it without any quarrelling againſt it, or queſtioning of it; let the ſoule bee delivered up to the will of God. As <hi>Da vid</hi> ſaid, <hi>Let my will be one with thine:</hi> when the Lord calls, ſeeke my face, wee ſhould echo, <hi>thy Face Lord I ſeeke:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19.</note> wee ſhould bee <hi>prepared for the Lord,</hi> ſo to have our affections ſtrike as the Lord ſets them; then wee ſhould doe his will a right, then
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59096:51"/>would it bee in our hearts to doe the will of God, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.</p>
                  <p>4. Wee ſhould have a couragious conſtant reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to goe on with that worke and in that way God hath revealed to us and hath laid open before us, ſo that the ſoule ſhould ſay, not my will, but give mee an heart to doe thy will: thus we ſhould have a conſtant reſolution to goe on, not to doe it by fits and ſtarts, but as the Apoſtle ſaith, fight the good fight of faith, and lay hold on eternall life; and except a man have this, he prayeth not this petition aright, but out of hypocriſie; it is his owne
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59096:51"/>will, hee ſeekes not the will of the Lord:now wee come to the ſecond thing: as wee ſhould doe the will of God our ſelves, ſo wee ſhould further others, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi>h appeares in 2. particulars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. We ſhould further o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in diſcharge of duty.</item>
                     <item>2. We ſhould joine ſides with others in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of duty.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. For the 1. <hi>To further others,</hi> that is a pregnant place <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>provoke one another to love, and good works,</hi> not only ſtand by &amp; looke on others, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke &amp; egge on, &amp; ſtir up others to doe the will of the Lord. The Lord there commends the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.3.</note> becauſe they gave
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59096:52"/>good examples to their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; It is good to have a ſtirring heart. Sathan ſets on others to ſinne; <hi>a little leaven, leavens the whole lump;</hi> a man uſeth not to be drunke alone, but to draw on others with him; If Sathan and his inſtruments bee ſo in evill, how much more ought we to doe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary good?</p>
                  <p>There is not a duty that more promotes Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry then this: wicked men as leaprous perſons labor to infect others, ſo ſhould wee bee forwards to help others; they provoke their fellow ſervants, and goe about reproving, exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another:So ſhould
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59096:52"/>a Chriſtian ſet on every man, and ſpurre on others to doe the will of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Labour likewiſe to joine ſides with them that doe Gods will; It was the practiſe of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> to lay hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy loads and burdens up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others, but not ſtirre themſelves; but we ſhould lend our helping hand in the performance of duty; when a Cart is at a ſet, it is not enough to ſtand by and ſay; I would it were out, and yet never lend a helping hand, but joyne with others to help it out: and if one teame will not doe, put another to it.</p>
                  <p>So when another is not able to get out by reaſon
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59096:53"/>of temptation, then wee muſt joyne with him and pray &amp; mourne with him. <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.21. <hi>Let us goe to the houſe of the Lord, and wee will goe alſo:</hi> it is not enough to profeſſe our ſelves Gods ſervants, but wee muſt pray and ſuffer alſo if need requires. It was <hi>Davids</hi> ſpeech, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. <hi>Let us prayſe the Lord together,</hi> ſo if wee would doe Gods will, it is not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to pray our ſelves, but wee muſt quicken o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to pray and ſtudy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. It is not enough to wiſh that Gods will might bee done, and wee ſtand by, with our hands in our pockets, and doe not provoke on others, but
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59096:53"/>lay reproaches on them; what you pray? I tell you ſuch a heart is profeſſedly againſt the will of God: Theſe are ſchollers of the higheſt forme in Sathans ſchoole: if ever we deſire to effect Gods will, let us ſet our ſhoulders to the burden, and help others, all wee can: thus much for the third petition, Thy will bee done.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Give us this day our daily Bread.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>4.</hi> Petition.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee come now to the other three petitions, and they concerne our ſelves; the firſt is, concerning the things of this life, and the other two concerning ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall gifts; and it conſiſts partly in <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59096:54"/>in <hi>Sanctification.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> But firſt, for the <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> why doe wee beg for the things of this life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpirituall mercies, our bodily bread before our ſpirituall Bread?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe in nature a man muſt have an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward being here before wee have a better: this life is the time of our tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and after this life there is no grace to bee had; therefore wee muſt have this life before wee can live everlaſtingly with God hereafter; no man can get good by the meanes that doth not live; therefore though the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee more neceſſary, yet a man except he have
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59096:54"/>this, cannot have the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that living here bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, we may live ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually hereafter: Now for the ſenſe of the words.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. What is meant by <hi>giving.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. What is meant by <hi>Bread,</hi> with al the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, <hi>dayly</hi> bread, and <hi>our</hi> daily <hi>bread.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>For the firſt, the word giving implies 3. things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That the Lord out of his goodneſſe and wiſe bounty, would provide what may bee profitable for us, and which we ſtand in need of; in a word, that hee would ſupply what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we want.</item>
                     <item>2. That hee would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thoſe good things
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59096:55"/>hee hath beſtowed upon us, that hee would graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly continue our lot and portion unto us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. <hi>Thou maintaineſt my lot.</hi> The Lord doth not onely give a patrimony to his children, but preſerves and continues that which is needfull to them.</item>
                     <item>3. That the Lord would bee pleaſed to ſend in the ſweet of his bleſſings and mercies hee hath beene pleaſed to beſtow on us; the bleſſing of the Lord is the ſtaffe of bread. It is not enough to have theſe bleſſings, for bread may choake us; the houſes wee inhabite may fall upon our heads, if they be not bleſſed to us. The cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59096:55"/>is as if hee had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if the Lord let in but a ſecret curſe and veine of vengeance into his ſoule: a man may have many outward bleſſings, and yet have all the ſweetneſſe tooke off from them, that many times all that a man hath, may bee a torment unto him: the Lord can take off all the ſweet, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we pray and entreate that the Lord would give us the ſweet of them, that they may be comfortable to us, as they are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q</hi> What is meant by <hi>bread?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Under this word bread, are included all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary helps and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59096:56"/>of this life, what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver concernes our <hi>lives, good name</hi> or <hi>eſtate,</hi> all things belonging to theſe, is <hi>bread.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Becauſe <hi>bread</hi> is the ſtaffe of life, moſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially uſefull for life: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things are neceſſary, but a man cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this bread, therefore the Lord puts a part for the whole, it including, all bleſſings neceſſary for us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q</hi> What kind of bread muſt it be?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. Our bread,</hi> not that wee can procure or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe; but the word <hi>our,</hi> implies, that theſe things may bee ours in way of right, betweene man and man, that wee may not
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59096:56"/>have them by violence, not to have another mans riches and honours, but that wee have a right to the ſame by the ſweat of our owne browes; not to pluck it from them, but that it may bee ours by our <hi>labour, meanes, patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is meant by <hi>daily?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The word in the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſignifies <hi>ſubſtantiall bread,</hi> and not barely ſo much food and cloathes as will keepe the life and ſoule together, and no more; but that wee may have to our lawfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, as one ſpake, ſo much as will keep even at the years end.</p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:59096:57"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q</hi> Why <hi>this day?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It implies 3. things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. A daily need of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour that wee have from the Lord; we doe not ſay give us this month or this quarter, but give us <hi>this day,</hi> as who ſhould ſay, wee ſtand in need of a daily ſuccour from the Lord: the Lord would not have a Chriſtian have too much, leaſt he might be ſecure, as the rich man in the Goſpell, <hi>ſoule take thine eaſe;</hi> thou haſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough now: but the Lord would have us come for our breakfaſt, dinner and ſupper, and all from him.</item>
                     <item>2. It ſhewes that a man muſt bee content with his allowance, his deſires
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59096:57"/>ſhould not bee catching after future things; wee beg not for our monthly and quarterly bread, but <hi>dayly bread,</hi> enough for the preſent time.</item>
                     <item>3. It implies that wee muſt pray for this dayly bread, <hi>every day</hi> a man muſt be begging and cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Lord, this is the meaning of this day: gather then up all and, the ſumme returnes to thus much; wee in this petition beſeech the Lord that all good things that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne life, good name or food, may bee ſupplied to us, that wee may have more then barely enough, not to wring from others, to bee content with the leaſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59096:58"/>pittance, and dayly and continually to begge for thoſe things we want and ſtand in need of.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q</hi> What is the frame of the heart in the putting up of this petition?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It appeares in three things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. A painefulneſſe with care in that courſe and calling which God calls him to, and ſets him in.</item>
                     <item>2. An humble depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on God.</item>
                     <item>3. A quiet contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with that God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. For the firſt, he muſt bee painefull; no man can ſay, <hi>give mee this day my daily bread,</hi> unleſſe hee be painefull in his place; if
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59096:58"/>wee expect any thing any otherwiſe, its a mocking of God; wee muſt bee faithfull in our places, if wee expect any <hi>honour, goods,</hi> or <hi>good name.</hi> It was the Command God gave <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>In the ſweat of thy browes ſhalt thou eat thy bread all the dayes of thy life;</hi> there is no allowance for idleneſſe and careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the Lord <hi>ſets Adam to till the ground;</hi> ſo that if wee expect any thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for us, we muſt take paines: for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>hee that will not labour let him not eat;</hi> the diligent hand makes rich.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> But God makes rich you will ſay.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> It is true, by a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59096:59"/>hand, a ſcholler muſt labour if hee will have learning: looke as it is with a man that hath promiſed another ſo much, and ſo much at ſuch a time, and ſuch a place, if hee will come for it; now if the man comes not for it, hee looſeth it; Even ſo it is here, the Lord promiſeth ſucceſſe to our labour, the Lord bleſſeth the plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by his plow, the trades-man by his trade, the ſcholler in his ſtudy; but except wee bee paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in our places, wee can expect nothing: the Lord gives us our daily bread, while we walke with him: ſo that a man hinders him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more by idleneſſe
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59096:59"/>than hee profits himſelfe by prayer, without <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ſoule muſt have a dependance on God, when it hath done what it can: a man ſhould be ſo painefull in the uſe of the meanes, as though they could doe all, and yet ſo depend upon God above the meanes, as though all outward meanes, could not doe any good without the Lord; wee muſt not catch it out of Gods hands but looke to God in the way hee hath chalked out before us, and then expect of him what wee want; It is the Lord, that gives a man ſubſtance; In vaine it is, to riſe earely in the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:59096:60"/>morning and to goe to bed late, and eat the bread of carefulneſſe, except the Lord bleſſe all, all is in vaine.</p>
                  <p>Let us looke therefore unto him for all we ſtand in need of; It is the phraſe of the wiſe man. <hi>The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Lord makes rich,</hi> it is not policie, craft and outward means that make rich, but the bleſſing of the Lord: from that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect all: though the plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man plow, though the gardner manure, cut and prune, yet nothing thrives unleſſe the dew of heaven falls: ſo it is here in our courſes, all our labours, paines, meanes and coſt, though it bee much and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59096:60"/>great, yet it wil not thrive unleſſe the Lord bleſſe; <hi>The Spirit of the Lord mo ved on the waters, Geneſ.</hi> 2. Let us therefore looke to his bleſſing upon all: a ſcholler may labour and take much paines, and yet ſhal never attaine his ends; either hee ſhall not have it at all, or if he have, it ſhalas <hi>Vriahs letter</hi> choak him at laſt; except we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on God, all labour and paines is nothing.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. There muſt bee a quiet contentednes, with what God beſtowes, and we receive, elſe we croſſe our ſelves: wee pray for bread, would wee then have what wee liſt? Wee doe not pray for dainties
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59096:61"/>and coſtlineſſe of apparel, but for bread that pittance the Lord ſhall be pleaſed to beſtow upon us: now if nothing but dainties and curioſities will ſerve us, it is more than the word al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, &amp; then we can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to bee beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us. If wee have meate and cloth, wee muſt not looke to the quantity ſo much, a month or a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but goe to the Lord, and let him diſpoſe of all, or elſe wee beg one thing and deſire another.</p>
                  <p>The Lord will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to give us bread, not pearles; not to cocker us, but to give us what wee ſtand in need of. That of <hi>Agar, give mee not too much
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59096:61"/>leaſt I bee proud; nor too little, leaſt I put forth my hand to wickednes; but give me food convenient;</hi> ſhowes it is better to bee at Gods allowance then our owne: A child happily would have a coate foure or five yards long to tire him, and fire to burne him, but a father will not have it, for feare of harming him.</p>
                  <p>So wee would flow o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but our Father mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures out our portions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our need. It is with us as with dieted ſick men, they would have hot wines, and ſalt meats, and eat exceſſively, but the Phyſitian orders all their dyets; for if they ſhould have their fill, it
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59096:62"/>would kill them, a full ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack would encreaſe the humour; ſo the Lord is a marvellous skilfull Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian; wee have proud, hauty hearts, and would have dainties, and if wee ſhould have riches as wee would, God ſhould looſe his honour which now he hath by us beeing kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hatches, therefore the Lord diets us: nothing would ſerve ſome, if the Lord ſhould not ſtint the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but they would bee as proud and ſaucy as ever they could; therefore the Lord is compelled to diet them: thus wee ſhould be content with the leaſt pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that the Lord ſees fit for us: and hee that is
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59096:62"/>thus the Lord will give him enough for his baite in this his pilgrimage; and ſo much for this peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And forgive us our treſpaſſes, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the fift petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, touching the good of man, three concerning God, and three concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning us, this life and a better: the firſt wee have handled, and they that concerne our ſpirituall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing follow. Wherein ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The <hi>Order.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The <hi>Senſe</hi> and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words.</item>
                     <item>3. The <hi>frame of the heart</hi> in putting up this petition.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:59096:63"/>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>order,</hi> why it is thus placed, namely <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification</hi> before <hi>Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi> the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Sanctification</hi> flowes from <hi>Iuſtification;</hi> Being juſtified, we are ſanctified: firſt, wee are acquitted of our ſinnes, whereof wee ſtand guilty before God, and then hee ſanctifies us: firſt this, then the other; the other are the ſprings, &amp; this the maine branch: wee beg for faith and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces, but all are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in this.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As for the ſence of the words, take notice.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Here is the petition, <hi>Forgive us our treſpaſſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The reaſon, <hi>as wee forgive others,</hi> or, for even
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59096:63"/>as we forgive others, that treſpaſſe againſt us, ſo Lord forgive thou our debts: this is the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereby we winne the favour of the Lord.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is meant by <hi>debts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By <hi>debts</hi> are meant all ſinnes, all failings, whether of <hi>omiſſion</hi> or <hi>commiſſion:</hi> Now they are called <hi>debts,</hi> becauſe wee owe all kind of obedience to God, to love him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as our ſelves. Now theſe being the articles of agreement, the ſlighting &amp; neglect of this ſame brings us into debt with God.</p>
                  <p>For firſt, we are bound to theſe: Secondly, by
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59096:64"/>breaking theſe wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the puniſhment due to the breach of it: now when wee omit any thing we forfeit and are caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind hand. Thirdly, wee are liable to the execution of the puniſhment due for the breach of this. Thus all ſins are debts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is it to <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To forgive is this; wee beg that the Lord would bee pleaſed not to take advantage of us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our debts; nor yet to proceed in the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the Law to doe that it requires. Now our ſinnes require wee ſhould bee condemned and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted: a malefactor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:59096:64"/>his bond is caſt in his cauſe, throwne into priſon, and execution ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his debt: Now wee beg of the Lord, that hee would not condemne us in the Court of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, nor execute his Juſtice on us: this is to forgive, and this proceeds from mercy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> But how can God doe this? will this ſtand with the Juſtice of God, not to bee ſatisfied for our facts; to pardon them without ſatisfaction for them?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No, but though the party doe not ſatisfy, yet if the ſurety doe, it is ſufficient; ſo though hee
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59096:65"/>forgive us, yet hee lookes for it at the ſureties hand. As the Creditor doth not require the debt at the debtors hands, yet hee doth at his hands that is bound to make ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the ſame; ſo the Lord doth not require ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of us, as hee might, to exact the utmoſt farthing; becauſe thou ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thou ſhalt die: the Lord will not exact this of us, but he requires this ſatisfaction of the Lord Jeſus. So that God the Father is ſatisfied though not by us, therein ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy on my part, and Juſtice on Chriſts part: thus wee ſee what it is to forgive, that the Lord
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59096:65"/>would not arreſt me, but the ſurety; that he would not exact of me, but take all of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For we forgive others.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is made an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to prevaile with God: wee beſeech God to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us: becauſe wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give others: as who ſhould ſay, If we forgive others, forgive thou us; as though firſt we could not forgive others before God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us, hence the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on drawes on, namely,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Whether is the ſoule able to forgive treſpaſſes to others, before the Lord forgive its treſpaſſes?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No, our forgiving others doth not goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our owne forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:59096:66"/>God muſt firſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us before wee can forgive others, becauſe it is a worke of grace to doe this as God requires, and it comes from a gracious diſpoſition of ſoule which God muſt put in us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee can doe it, for ſanctification followes Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. Now to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give treſpaſſes is a worke of obedience, flowing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanctification, which ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification followes Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; as a man ſhould ſay, a tree brings forth fruit from the ſappe in the roote.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> But this is uſed as a <hi>cauſe:</hi> we forgive others, <hi>therefore</hi> forgive thou us, it ſeemes.</p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:59096:66"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No, it is a fruit and effect to make way for this conveiance and aſſurance: it makes us not to bee juſt, but declares us to be juſt: every reaſon propounded by the word, becauſe it doth not imply a cauſe; as I proove fire to bee fire thus: that which burnes is fire, but that burnes, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is fire: now burning is not the cauſe of fire, but an effect of it, for firſt there muſt bee fire before it can burne: ſo it is a tree becauſe it beares apples: now apples are not the cauſe of the tree, but the tree of the fruit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is it to forgive the treſpaſſes of our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low brethren, and how
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59096:67"/>farre may wee doe it?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In the treſpaſſe of a brother three things are conſiderable.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The <hi>ſinne</hi> it ſelfe.</item>
                     <item>2. The <hi>guilt</hi> of that ſin.</item>
                     <item>3. The <hi>puniſhment</hi> due to that ſinne.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Concerning the ſin and guilt, wee muſt know two things, wherein is the anſwer.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. We muſt know, that to forgive properly wee cannot, it cannot be done by us, for who can forgive ſinnes but God onely? it is one of Gods preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to forgive ſinnes, and no creature can doe the ſame.</item>
                     <item>2. As the <hi>guilt</hi> hath a reſpect to God, ſo it hath
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59096:67"/>a reſpect to us; for as he is injured, ſo are we; when a man ſteales, it is not onely a wrong to the Law of God, but alſo a wrong to mee: ſo farre as the ſinne doth reſpect God, he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneth it, and as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes mee, I forgive him; and this is done when the heart is as willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to doe all good to a brother, as though hee had never ſinned againſt him: wee ſay wee forgive him, but wee will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get him: this is not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, but when betweene him and mee there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſtop the doing of good, this is true forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Whether is a man
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:59096:68"/>bound to forgive <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to another, as when one hath ſtollen any thing from us, ſhould wee not follow the law on him? how farre muſt a man goe in this caſe in taking pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment on ſuch an one offending?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A man may, nay it may bee ſo, that a man is bound not to forgive it, but to puniſh it; and a man ſhould ſinne deeply in the neglect of it. If a man hath murthered another, a man is bound to follow the law on him, and to give him the puniſhment due to the fact.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How farre may a man goe in this caſe?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It appeares in theſe particulars.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:59096:68"/>1. When all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered a man ſees it may doe good, then hee is bound to give puniſhment: when there is nothing but a bridewell will doe a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant good, give it him; when a child is ſtubborne, give him correction and ſpare him not; It is as good as his meate: If a wretch belch out his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, if a man can reforme him by puniſhment, give it him, who knowes but it may be the beſt Phyſicke that hee ever had? and to let him goe unpuniſhed in ſuch a caſe makes a man guilty of his ſinne, becauſe he might have reformed him by this meanes.</p>
                  <p>2. If this bee a way and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:59096:69"/>meanes to bind a mans hand, and to hinder him from the practiſe of ſome ſinne; if a man have a ſuite of law againſt him, hee is bound to caſt him into priſon, for that keeps him from ſinning deepely. It is a worke of mercy to take a knife from a mad man; ſo GOD put an opportunity into a mans hands, hee is bound to take the Law, and it is mercy to him thus to doe.</p>
                  <p>3. When a man cannot otherwiſe maintaine his owne honour, life or ſome other particular good, for the taking off his owne wrong, a man is bound in Juſtice ſo to doe; as thus, if one ſhould raiſe a falſe
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:59096:69"/>report upon a man, it is not a worke of Tyranny, but a worke of mercy; hee ought to right his owne wrong by puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when it cannot be otherwiſe maintained: we are bound to take this courſe, for why? mine owne honour, life, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is to bee preferred before others.</p>
                  <p>4. When this courſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Juſt, will maintaine the goodneſſe of a mans profeſſion and Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, this ſhould bee done; when a mans profeſſion lyes at the ſtake, a man is bound to be meale mouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but to mak thoſe black-mouthed wretchesknown to others, that they may
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:59096:70"/>not dare to bring a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall upon the glorious go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of Chriſt, nor on the profeſſours thereof: thus a man muſt doe, and yet forgive a man for all this, if his good or mine, or the profeſſion of the Goſpell may be furthered thereby: and thus farre a man may goe in theſe caſes and the like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Now wee come to the force of the argument: how is this an argument to prevaile with God to <hi>forgive us,</hi> becauſe <hi>we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give others,</hi> where lies the force of the argument, what vertue is there in this?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It lies in three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, this being a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:59096:70"/>meanes to obteine mercy; <hi>Lord I forgive o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> therfore <hi>forgive thou mee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. All the mercy I have is not firſt in my ſelfe, it is but a river and ſpring co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the ſea; but mercy is firſt in thy ſelfe, O Lord, the fountaine and ſea of mercy is in thee; Now Lord if I have but ſome bowells of mercy and ſome drops of that Ocean of thy mercy, and yet can forgive others, much more then thou the fountaine of mercy canſt forgive me.</p>
                  <p>The ſervants you know, fel out, and the one pulled the other by the throat, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>pay me that thou oweſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:59096:71"/>me;</hi> now when the maſter heard of it, he ſaid, <hi>a thou wretch, doſt thou deale thus with him, when I dealt ſo favourably with thee?</hi> if a ſinner muſt forgive his brother 77. times, how much more the God of mercy? if hee that had but ſome mercy received from the fountaine, how much more the Lord the fountaine?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As wee have it not from our ſelves, but from God; ſo alſo that we have is mixt with a great deale of ſpleene; though ſome compaſſion, yet mingled with a great deale of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy; though ſome mercy, yet mingled with a great deale of cruelty: there is
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:59096:71"/>a great deale of darkenes with this little ſtar-light: but the Lord hath all love without any hatred, all mercy without any cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, there is no hinderance in the Lord to hinder him: Now the ſoule ſaith, Lord, if I that have a great deale of malice can forgive my brethren, then how much more thou that haſt all mercy and no ſpleene wilt forgive, if men humble their foules before thee?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That mercy that is in us, is but little; but it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit in the Lord: what we can doe is but the firſt fruit, a drop, a graine, a muſtard ſeed, but abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in the Lord: the ſoule
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:59096:72"/>ſaith, Lord thou art boundleſſe and bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in mercy, how much more wilt thou forgive? true, Lord, the talents &amp; debts whereby wee are engaged unto thee are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp; great; but yet if wee poore creatures that have but from the fountaine, &amp; that wee have is mingled with a great deale of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and that but a drop, and yet can forgive, how much more thou that haſt all firſt from thy ſelfe, and purely without all mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of envy, and in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite abundance, how much more canſt thou forgive whom thou wilt? therfore Lord forgive us, for we forgive others.</p>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:59096:72"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How ought the ſoule to bee framed in the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of this petition?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It appeares in foure particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The ſoule muſt ſee and acknowledge it ſelfe guilty of thoſe ſinnes that appeare in his life: wee muſt ſee our ſelves ſtand in need of forgiveneſſe; now wee cannot doe this till we ſee our ſelves faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; he that owes nothing, what need hee crave for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe? ſo <hi>forgiveneſſe of ſinnes</hi> implies, that we are guilty thereof, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the puniſhment due to ſinne.</p>
                  <p>They that confeſſe ſin and forſake it, ſhall find mercy. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.14. firſt
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:59096:73"/>find thy ſinnes, then find Gods mercy.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>If we would judge our ſelves, we ſhould not bee judged:</hi> hee that would have God forgive him, muſt not forgive himſelfe; as a malefactor that ſtickes to his owne innocency, and will not acknowledge any guilt, in vaine hee deſires to bee forgiven, ſo a ſinner is a malefactor before Gods tribunall: now if hee will not confeſſe, he ſhal never find mercy at the hand of the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Wee muſt labour to have the heart ſee its own inability to ſatisfy for ſin, or to beare Gods Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hee ſhall paſſe upon the ſoule that is guilty: the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:59096:73"/>ſoule acknowledgeth it ſelfe unable to anſwer one of a thouſand. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>Lord if thou ſhouldſt enter into Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who were able to abide it? but there is mercy with thee, that thou maiſt be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> We are banquerouts, wee cannot anſwer the debt, nor beare the ſuite: if the debtor bee able to anſwer the debt, or pay the money, hee cares for no kindneſſe.</p>
                  <p>The ſinner is the deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and if I can ſatisfie Gods Juſtice, what need I care? if I can abide it, what need I crave favor? but when it comes to this, <hi>who can abide it?</hi> then it is the LORD muſt pardon
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:59096:74"/>what ever is amiſſe; where ever the ſinner goes, hee cannot avoid the ſuite, he needs no purſevant to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him: conſcience is arreſting, and the Divell accuſing, therefore hee fals downe and cries mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, mercy to pardon the ſuite; the ſoule is not able to beare the ſuite, the Church complaines of it, behold our righteouſneſſe is as a menſtruous cloth, and they <hi>Ezeoh.</hi> 36.31. judge themſelves worthy to bee condemned: now in that I ſay forgive, I ſay I cannot ſatisfy for my ſinne.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Wee ſhould ſeeke to God and his grace, for what we need; we ſhould
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:59096:74"/>knowledge it his free mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; when the ſoule ſees there is mercy in God for him, then it is fitted to pray for this petition. For ſhould I conceave God were ſevere, though I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced my ſinne, yet I could not ſeeke him: God is not extreame and rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, but hee hath mercy in ſtore for them that ſeek him in truth and ſincerity, therefore wee ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend two things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That God deſires not to deale rigorouſly, wee ſhould perſwade our harts that God is deſirous to welcome our prayers. The Lord is ſaid to bee <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in goodnes and mercy;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ex. 34.</note> the Lord is ready to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:59096:75"/>our infirmities. If we abound in miſery, the Lord will abound in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: the phraſe is, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying mercy, therefore the Apoſtle calls him, the Father of mercy and the God of all conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: wee have new vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he hath new compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, nay, God hath more good then we can deſire, hee performes more then promiſeth, hee is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in truth above all that hee hath revealed himſelfe to bee in his word, <hi>Iſay</hi> 55.7. Our God is mercifull and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant in forgiveneſſe, hee multiplies pardons, hee hath pardons in ſtore, mercie to pardon any
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:59096:75"/>poore ſoule, But ſaith the ſoule, what? my ſinnes committed and continued in? Marke what he adds, his thoughts of mercy are larger in giving then ours in craving. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. hee is able to doe above what wee can aske orthinke.</p>
                  <p>It was but cold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort <hi>Iſaac</hi> gave to <hi>Eſau,</hi> he had but <hi>one bleſſing:</hi> ſo if GODS mercies ſhould come to an end, it were but poore comfort: when the ſoule ſhould ſay Lord give mee, and the Lord ſhould ſay all is drawne dry; but there is enough in God to doe us good: what availes it though a father have a tender and a good heart
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:59096:76"/>to his child, if hee hath not to give it what it askes or ſtands in need of? but our heavenly father a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds in goodneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. God as hee hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of good, ſo hee is free and ready to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it. <hi>Iſay</hi> 55.1. <hi>Ho,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that thirſteth, let him buy milke and hony without money or price: wee would bee content to have wine, but wee have no money to buy it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God adds, though you bee not able to pay for it, yet take it. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18. Who is a God like our God, who pardons ſins, becauſe mercy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him? the pardoning of our ſinnes is like the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowing
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:59096:76"/>of Pharaoh in the ſea: God doth it not ſo much, becauſe wee pleaſe him, but becauſe his mercy pleaſeth him, he doth it freely.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Wee muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to waite for this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy wee ſtand in need of: wee muſt waite for it and be confidently perſwaded of it, elſe wee croſſe the tenure of forgivenes, <hi>Held.</hi> 11. God gives mercy to none but thoſe that waite for it: in that we aske par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, wee are reſolved to waite for it, (for ſo much is implied) a pardon in law is not authenticall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it bee ſealed. So God ſaith he, will pardon us: but this is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uthenticall
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:59096:77"/>untill wee have ſet to our ſeale; hee ſaith, hee will give freely, wee ſay, wee wil waite conſtantly. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.5. Commit thy waies to God, and hee will care for thee: hee that thus begs forgiveneſſe ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly obtaine it at the hand of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And lead us not into temptation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>6.</hi> Petition.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>This conſiſts of <hi>ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> both begun here and ended in <hi>glorification,</hi> ſanctification frees from the power of ſinne, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication frees from the preſence of ſinne.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For the <hi>order,</hi> ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication flowes from Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; when ſinne is pardoned we have the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:59096:77"/>of Chriſt which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyes all to us: we are firſt juſtified, then ſanctified.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For the <hi>ſence</hi> of the words, here are 2. things:
<list>
                        <item>1. What wee deſire God ſhould not doe, <hi>lead us not into temptation.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. What he ſhould doe, <hi>deliver us from evill.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is meant by temptation?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A triall or aſſault whereby a mans ſtrength is tried; now they are double.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Deliverance into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A proofe of the ſoundneſſe of grace: the firſt is eſpecially intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, all the aſſaults of the ſoule by ſinne, Sathan or
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:59096:78"/>the world wherby either our faith may be ſhaken or we withdrawn from God to evill: ſometimes there are good temptations of proving or expreſſing our grace; theſe in ſome ſence may have place in this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition: God tries us on this manner, and wee pray him that hee would not try us more then wee are able to beare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is it to bee <hi>led into temptation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. When temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons purſue us.</item>
                        <item>2. When they doe foile us aſſaulting of us.</item>
                        <item>3. When temptation doth totally vanquiſh us.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now wee pray in this petition, that <hi>temptations</hi>
                     <pb n="153" facs="tcp:59096:78"/>may not purſue us, or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing us, that they may not foile us, and though wee bee foiled by them, yet that wee may recover our ſelves; we deſire that corruptions would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege us, or if they doe, yet not conquer, but that we may recover our ſelves after we are overcome.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Can God lead into temptation?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines it <hi>I am.</hi> 1.13. <hi>God cannot tempt to evill,</hi> hee that is goodneſſe it ſelfe cannot provoke a man to ſinne: the Lord doth not put malice into any mans heart, God cannot bee properly the cauſe of drawing any man to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:59096:79"/>There are tryals of proofe indeed: the Lord may try <hi>his,</hi> as hee did <hi>Abraham. Gen.</hi> 22.1. A man doth not hurt his armour if it be good when as hee prooves it: ſo God intends no evill to a man when as hee thus deales with him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> In what manner doth God lead us into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Hee doth it three wayes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When the Lord withdrawes not thoſe nets that are laid for us: when GOD removes not our ſtumbling blocks: nay, God may put an object of temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before us. Thus a maſter may lay a baite
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:59096:79"/>for his ſervant by putting money in a corner; now it is lawfull thus, for a man to leave his money to diſcerne whether his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant be faithfull or no; he deſires not that he ſhould ſteale, but that he may try his fidelity. So God juſtly permitteth occaſions.</p>
                  <p>There muſt be <hi>hereſies</hi> for the <hi>triall</hi> of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. They that pitch their net firſt, let it fall, and then take it up, this is to raine ſnares. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is but a baite to a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man, his proſperity is his ruine; it is juſt with God to deale ſo, becauſe wicked men deſire it: So <hi>Iudas</hi> would faine have
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:59096:80"/>gotten ſomething by the ointment; it is juſt with God to ſuffer the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees to give him 30. pence and ruine too. Now his mind is pleaſed, hee hath 30<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. and damnation too.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As God ſuffers <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> ſo hee lets ſinne and Sathan looſe; a mans hart would faine bee hanker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and God gives him up to his hearts luſts ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>take him ſinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, let him have field roome.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.22. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> would faine goe to warre, it was a thing not allowed, but hee deſired it; therefore God ſends the Divell: God askes who will prevaile over <hi>Ahab?</hi> the Divell ſaith, <hi>I
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:59096:80"/>will goe:</hi> then God ſaith, <hi>goe and doe it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abimelech</hi> and the men of <hi>Sichem</hi> did very ill;<note place="margin">Jud. 9.23.</note> then God ſent an evill ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that is, hee let looſe the ſpirit of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and they deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and hee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to deſtroy them, ſo God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. is ſaid to give them up, when they departed from the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the truth: no, ſaith God, will you not be ruled by holines? then take <hi>uncleaneneſſe:</hi> many a man that hath a wrathfull diſpoſition, take him envy ſaith God, let him bring blood on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſo ruine to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: thus God tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:59096:81"/>his ſpirit from <hi>Saul,</hi> and gave him up to ſinfull diſtempers; of all plagues there is none that is like this.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. God leaves a man to himſelfe, and lendes him not the aſſiſtance of his grace, but ſuffers him and Sathan to grapple toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>Thus he dealt with <hi>He-Zechiah;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Chron. 32.31.</note> who becauſe he had a leaſe of his life, bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee proud: now God left him to himſelfe, to ſee what was in him; hee thought himſelfe a brave man, therfore God leaves him; as a father lets a child goe when hee will not be held, ſo ſaith God, ſee what thou canſt doe,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:59096:81"/>try thine owne ſtrength.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But deliver us from evill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence obſerve, that though God would doe nothing againſt us, yet we are not able to deliver our ſelves from our corrupt heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is meant by <hi>evill?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Not ſo much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or puniſhment, as <hi>ſin;</hi> in it are three things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The breach of the Law.</item>
                     <item>2. The guilt that a man gets by this breach, and ſo is liable to this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                     <item>3. The vigour of ſinne, which rules over the ſoule; the two former,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:59096:82"/>wee pray againſt, in the fifth <hi>petition;</hi> becauſe we ſtand guilty of the breach of the Law. Therefore wee pray that hee would not <hi>enter into judgement with us:</hi> wee pray <hi>now</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>power</hi> of ſin, and that is in three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Sinne</hi> would be a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander over the ſoule; it is the King, Sathan is the Jaylour; it hath a Kingly ſoveraigne authority and would rule over him: ſin is often compared to a King, his ſervants are his obeyers; ſinne is a maſter, (at leaſt it would bee) it is ſo in every naturall foule, and it would bee ſo in the godly: <hi>the law of life,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:59096:82"/>the Apoſtle, <hi>hath freed mee from the law of death. Rom.</hi> 8.2. ſinne gives par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament lawes and edicts to the ſoule; and as the <hi>Centurion</hi> bad one ſervant goe and hee went, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other come and hee came, ſo doth ſinne ſay, <hi>pride</hi> it is my pleaſure you ſhould bee proud, therefore I would have you imperiall and ſnappiſh: ſayes <hi>anger,</hi> I would have you ſplene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke and rage; ſayes the ſoule, then I will, it ſhall be done: thus ſinne ſets up it ſelfe as ſupreame in the ſoule: hence a proud heart ſaith, I will doe that I liſt, ſay God what hee will; tell not mee of lawes, it is my mind. Thus your
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:59096:83"/>proud heart ſets you lawes and you yeeld to them. Now wee pray here that how ſoever ſin bee in the ſoule, yet that God would ſnib it, that it may bee an underling, and daily bee ſubdued in us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As ſinne deſires to ſet up a maſter like rule, and a ſupreame, ſoveraigne Lord-like dominion, ſo ſinne carries the ſoule and ſometimes ſeparates it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God; whereas the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God ſhould be a guide to us and take place in our hearts, this autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity takes up armes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, and ſtands in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt the rule of the ſpirit; hence came theſe phraſes, <hi>they forſooke
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:59096:83"/>God, and turned their backs to his Commands.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What ſaith pride, ſhall I be a ſlave, that the world ſhould awe mee, and ſnub me? I will never yeeld it while I live, I will dye firſt: this is a Divell that drawes you from God and will carry you to hell, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23. That is the meaning of this place, ſin carries a man captive; when the ſoule ſees it ſelfe ſo ruled by him, a gratious hart would teare it ſelfe off if it could; but a naturall man is a ſlave to ſinne, and dares not affect any good in another nor labour for it himſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sinne leaves a kind of blemiſh and ſtaine upon
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:59096:84"/>the ſoule; after the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of it there is a kind of jarring to the heart and of running wrong in the ſoule. <hi>Peter</hi> after his deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of Chriſt was averted from Chriſt; ſo a man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinne ſhall find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo dull to any good and prone to any evil; this is the ſtaine of ſin: when a mans arme is put out of joint, beſides the fall there is a bruiſe, ſo after a man hath broken the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Lord, the law unjoints him, hee is more awke to any good then ever, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. If any man be unjointed by ſin, ſo that of the Romans, wound their owne ſoules, this ſin doth. Now theſe
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:59096:84"/>wee pray againſt, partly againſt the power of ſin, partly againſt the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſinne, partly againſt the ſtaine of ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But deliver us from evill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To <hi>deliver from evill</hi> implies three things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Wee pray that the Lord would preve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thoſe occaſions and ſtragglings of ſinne that trouble us; wee pray that hee would take off theſe diſtempers, whereby ſinne would lay ſiege againſt the ſoule, that hee would remove thoſe things that would remoove us from him. This wiſdome promiſeth. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.21. <hi>That ſhee will walke with them, that walke with her; ſhee will keep
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:59096:85"/>them from the way of the wicked woman:</hi> ſinne is like an harlot, therefore the Lord is pleaſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it after that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
                  <p>Now it is the mercy of God that hee will turne our eyes from beholding of vanity, that there may not bee violence of ſinne aſſaulting us, now wee pray therefore that wee may not come into the battaile, if it be poſſible: and that ſin may not come in againſt us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Lord would aſſiſt us in the temptation that the temptation may not prevaile. It is a mercy not to bee tempted; but if wee muſt needs bee, it
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:59096:85"/>is a great mercy not to be overcome by temptation; if he will not wholly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent us by his grace, yet to aſſiſt us gratiouſly in it: It is mercy not to bee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted, and though aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted yet aſſiſted.</p>
                  <p>Now this aſſiſtance of God is twofold; either extraordinary, or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, by the meanes: wee ſpeake not ſo much of the firſt, though that be true, but wee crave both at the hand of the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Sometimes we crave for the extraordinary help and aſſiſtance of the Lord, to aſſiſt us even above meanes &amp; in the meanes: wee know the Lord in the time of Queene <hi>Mary</hi> did
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:59096:86"/>help wonderfully; their temptations were grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, and afflictions great, yet the Lord did help them extraordinarily, hee did let in abundance of ſweetneſſe: but wee paſſe this, and come to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Wee pray eſpecially for ſuch meanes as may help us, and that appeares in foure particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the Lord would diſcover the enemy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee come, that hee would make knowne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us the engins, wiles and depths of Sathan, and the ſubtilty of our owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt hearts, which are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy on every hand to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize us. For to be ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:59096:86"/>before wee are aware is great danger. Therfore wee pray that the Lord would give us the ſpirit of <hi>Revelation,</hi> that wee may take notice of the engines of Sathan, and that hee may be diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us. The diſcovery (wee know) of an evill is a meanes to prevent it, &amp; not foreſeeing miſery, we cannot prevent it; he that ſees not an evill before it comes wil be overthrown by it when it comes: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a man periſheth by pride &amp; knowes not what hurts him; this corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on blowes up the ſoule. This the Lord promiſed, <hi>Iſay</hi> 30.21. Thou ſhalt heare a word behind thee
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:59096:87"/>ſaying this is the way; that GOD may keep a man from ſinne hee ſends the Spirit of Chriſt to ſay, this is the way, walke in it. The text ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. there ſpeaking of the ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous man, wee are not ignorant of the methods of Sathan: ſo we pray the Lord that hee would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the methods of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than to us. <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. When the great skirmiſh was to come, our Saviour forewarned <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; ſaid, I wil ſmite the ſhepheard, &amp;c. And ſaith, watch and pray; for the houre is come: hee gives him the warning peece: wee pray the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that God would make knowne to us the engines
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:59096:87"/>of ſinne and Sathan be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come. Wee know it is a great help in warre to know the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters &amp; orders of enemies, that ſo a man may order his according thereunto. So wee muſt know where the Divell and our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions lye quartered, &amp; know what be the haunts of our wretched harts, &amp; ſo order the helps God hath put into our hands for the reſiſting of them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Lord as it were, would entrench a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, if wee bee not foretold of the enemies; that if wee ſhould not ſee ſinne to prevent it, yet that God would lay ſome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy impediment upon us,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:59096:88"/>and build ſome trench a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, that wee may not commit thoſe evills wee are tempted unto; that though hee doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale the policy of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, yet that hee would lay ſome ſnares that wee may not commit that ſin w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> otherwiſe wee would doe: and this is a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous mercy, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Abimelech</hi> tooke <hi>Sarah</hi> and thought ſhe had been <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſiſter, as hee himſelfe told him; and no queſtion hee had a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to take her to be his wife, but the Lord laid an impediment, the LORD kept <hi>Abimelech</hi> from <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah;</hi> hee tooke off the edge of his deſire and laid
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:59096:88"/>a barre betweene them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.6.7. The Church was running after her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations: now how did the Lord prevent her? The text ſaith, <hi>I will hedge thy wayes with thornes, and build a wall about thee:</hi> the lovers were corruptions, and the following of them was the eager purſuite of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now God hedges the wayes with thornes, that is, hee layes afflictions on her, that ſhe had no liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſinne, ſo that ſhee hath enough to doe, to mind her owne miſeries: ſometimes a man is addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to baſe company, and then the Lord layes ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe upon him to priſon him and keep him from
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:59096:89"/>that ſinne, this is Mercy.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Lord puts ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and weapons on them, to fight againſt their enemies that are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to his grace and children. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. from the 10. to the 18. bee yee ſtrengthned in all might putting on all ſpirituall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, to bee ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in every good worke: God ſaith, hee covers the head of his. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 15. God keepes them by the power of his grace: God gives his the whole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, the ſword of faith, the breſt plate of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes to quench the firy darts of Sathan, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. God gives a domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:59096:89"/>over and a conqueſt of all our enemies, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all our victorious cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions: hee gives a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py iſſue and ſucceſſe with the fight, hee gives iſſues with the victory, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. <hi>hee hath made us Kings,</hi> that is, hee hath given us a <hi>Kingly authority</hi> over all our corruptions. So <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>ſinne ſhall not have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over you: and Pſal.</hi> 119.133. <hi>Let no iniquity have dominion over mee:</hi> thus the Lord aſſiſts his in trouble.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As wee pray that the Lord would prevent the occaſions of evill, and if they come to aſſiſt us in them: So laſtly, if we bee <hi>foyled</hi> and brought under
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:59096:90"/>by the temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and our owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, that the Lord would reſcue us from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that have had too much power over us, and too too much prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us. This wee know was the requeſt and deſire of the Prophet <hi>David. Pſal.</hi> 39. <hi>O ſpare me, that I may recover ſtrength, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I goe away hence and bee no more ſeene:</hi> as who ſhould ſay, my baſe luſts are too ſtrong for mee; Theſe hands were ſtout, but now feeble, therefore good Lord give mee that former ſtrength: his ſins were as ſickeneſſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee ſaith, I knew the time when I had a broken
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:59096:90"/>heart for my tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but now a hardned; therefore O Lord, ſpare mee a little while before I goe hence and be no more ſeene, that I may reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my former zeale and ſtrength againe.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.2.</note> 
                     <hi>The law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt, hath made mee free from the Law of ſin and death,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> Sinne makes Lawes, but we entreate the Lord that hee would prevent corruption, that he would aſſiſt us in temptations or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, that hee would diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the enemy before hee come, that hee would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench about us, vouchſafe us armour and weapons to reſiſt, &amp; give us dominion
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:59096:91"/>over our enemies, and if we bee overcome, that he would reſcue and recover us out of them all: this is the ſumme of this petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Now wee come to the frame of heart that wee ſhould bring before God, that ſo wee may bee fit to receive the good wee ſue for, from his hands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Firſt, wherein doth this appeare?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The frame of heart and diſpoſition of ſoule that beſt beſeemes us in the putting up of this peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion appeares principally in foure things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When wee truly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that the Lord would not let us bee drawne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> or lead into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:59096:91"/>we muſt labour to auoid all ſuch occaſions as may be too ſtrong for us, or prevaile over us. In vaine wee deſire to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from evill, when wee ruſh into evill; as if a man ſhould take pitch into his hands and deſire not to bee defiled, or put fire into his boſome and pray not to be burnt; this is a ſlighting of Gods mercy and provoking of him to wrath, rather then a begging of favour.</p>
                  <p>Wee would count it a madnes for a man to caſt himſelfe into the ſea, and then deſire to bee ſaved, to make our ſelves ſicke, that God may make us whole againe; it is nothing
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:59096:92"/>elſe but (as wee may ſay ſo) to make God worke: thus to run into evill and then to pray the Lord, hee would deliver us from evill, it is a provoking &amp; mocking of the Lord: the wiſe mans rule is here me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. If a man bee given to his appetite, <hi>Let him put a knife to his throate;</hi> if thou loveſt the wine, looke not upon it: if a man be given to his appetite, it is in vaine to pray againſt it; &amp; yet cate, but <hi>put thy knife to thy throate,</hi> abſteine therefrom: pleaſe not thy appetite.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>promiſe</hi> and the <hi>providence</hi> of God goe together,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.</note> hee will ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:59096:92"/>and relieve us, but it muſt bee in the way of his providence: hee that goes out of the way, and craves Gods aſſiſtance, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have it, but hales on evill to himſelfe. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. Our Saviour ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of offences, ſaith, <hi>If thy hand cauſe thee to offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, cut it off, and if thy eye cauſe thee to offend plucke it out,</hi> that is, were thy ſinnes as deare to thee as thy right hand in regard of profit, or thy right eye in regard of pleaſure, cut them off, pluck them out, fling them away rather then bee foiled by them. In vaine wee crave the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Lord, and in the meane time lay
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:59096:93"/>blocks before us, It is meere preſumption.</p>
                  <p>No marvell then if ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times the Lord leaves a man, becauſe hee ſtrives not after that hee prayes for. It is enough to cauſe the Lord to curſe us, when wee doe not avoid the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of evill; hee that will not fall into the pit, let him not come neere the brinke of it; hee that will not be ſnared by evil, let him ſhunne, and avoid all the occaſions of evill.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If wee bee weake of our ſelves and cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the occaſions of evil, yet bee carefull to ſeeke all ſuch meanes as may be ſuccourable and holpefull to us; if wee cannot help
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:59096:93"/>out, theſe wil ſurprize us. Let us ſeeke the meanes to ſuccour us in our need: the ſicke man that craves ſuccour of the Lord muſt uſe the meanes the Lord hath appointed; happily thou findeſt temptations preſſing on in thy calling, thou canſt not avoid it: the more the occaſions are, the more ſeeke for meanes that may fortifie thee; hee that will bee healed let him ſeeke the Phyſician; hee that is out of the way and would bee ſet in the right way, let him enquire it out, and not ſit ſtill and ſay, Lord have mercy upon mee, but ſeeke.</p>
                  <p>It was that which <hi>Ioſhua</hi>
                     <pb n="184" facs="tcp:59096:94"/>did;<note place="margin">Joſ. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>he called,</hi> yet the Lord did not help him, but ſaid, <hi>Why doſt thou ſo? Iſrael hath ſinned, looke out the execrable thing.</hi> Iſrael hath ſinned, looke to that; It is in vaine to pray that the enemy may not prevaile, if wee labour not to roote him out of the Camp; doe that throughly, and then the overthrow of thine enemies will be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy to thee.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. When we have found the meanes, labour to bee content to bee ordered by all the meanes and helps that God hath been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ordaine for our good. It is a madneſſe to crave as <hi>Balaam, Oh that I might dye,</hi> &amp;c. and yet
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:59096:94"/>ſee the way, and will not walke in it. <hi>Ier.</hi> 42. They ſaid to the Prophet, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at the word of the Lord, and what ever hee commandeth we wil do; but when they heard and knew it, they would not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the ſame.</p>
                  <p>In vaine it is to crave the pardon of ſinne, when we looke not to the promiſe; to deſire ſinne to bee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, &amp; yet cannot abide the meanes that ſhould doe it. When a man ſaith, I will not be counſelled, but will have my proud heart and will walke in mine owne wayes, how can ſuch a one ſay, deliver me from this proud heart, when he wil not let coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:59096:95"/>take place? when a man is in horror of heart, when conſcience flyes in his face, it is in vaine to whine then, and yet wilt not thou bee ruled by the word of God, but doe as vaine as ever, as looſe as ever, as idle as ever: thou beggeſt one thing &amp; doſt practiſe another thing, &amp; ſo long let us never put up this petition.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. We muſt rely on the Lord for a bleſſing on all, a ſucceſſe in all, ſo uſe the meanes as if there were no promiſe to help and yet ſo depend upon God for all, as if the meanes could doe nothing, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all thy occaſions, &amp; ſay counſell and advice is
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:59096:95"/>good, but the Lord muſt ſet them on; man lives not by bread onely, but by the bleſſing of God in the meanes; goe to the ſpirit of the Lord, and ſee there a greater power then in all meanes;<note place="margin">2 Kings 2.</note> 
                     <hi>If thou canſt ſee mee taken up, then ſhalt thou have my ſpirit doubled upon thee.</hi> If thou ſeeſt the God that takes mee up, then hee wil give thee his Spirit; looke to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all meanes, and hee that is thus diſpoſed, that man prayes aright to bee delivered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For thine is the Kingdome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We have done with the ſix petitions, three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God his name, Kingdome, will, three
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:59096:96"/>concerning our ſelves, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning things of this life, of a better, Juſtification, Sanctification: wee come now to the concluſion, and in it conſider two things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. The thankſgiving.</item>
                        <item>2. The concluſion of faith in the word <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
In the thankſgiving is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded both a reaſon of the petition, as alſo a forme of thankſgiving, as who ſhould ſay, wee doe not preſume wee can doe any thing, but that thou wouldeſt work in us what thou requireſt of us, for thine is the Kingdome. It is not in our power to doe what wee ſhould or what thou requireſt, but the Kingdome is thine, all
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:59096:96"/>comes from thee O Lord, and let all the glory of all bee returned to thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: doe wee hallow thy name and pray for thy Kingdome to come and thy will to be done? why it is thou Lord that muſt give the power; we beg all from him, and it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the word, for we have no power to doe any thing: ſo that this is the ground whereby wee beg all from him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne all to him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is here ment by Kingdome?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. The word King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome diſcovers all the right &amp; authority of God to give all things we want: thou Lord haſt the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:59096:97"/>of all things we have, no authoritie or proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that is in us, thine is the Kingdome, thou haſt all power to doe what thou wilt. The maſter doth what hee will in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and the King rules in his realme, ſo doth the Lord rule in the heart of his.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Lord hath not onely authority to doe what he will, but full and aboundant ſufficiency to diſpoſe of all according to his will and pleaſure, Kings may want power to doe what they would, and the ſonnes of <hi>Zerviah</hi> may bee too ſtrong for <hi>David;</hi> but as the Lord hath title to al, ſo his arme
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:59096:97"/>is large enough, his ability ſufficient enough to doe all; ſo that the ſoule ſaith, to doe all, thou haſt right to al, and ſufficiency to doe all. There is much infirmity in us, but none at all in thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The glory of a thing we know appeares in two things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. In the excellency of it.</item>
                     <item>2. In the beauty and ſplendour of its excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: this ſets forth the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of things, as who ſhould ſay, if any beauty, excellency or glory bee in the creature, it is thine O Lord, for thine is the
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:59096:98"/>Kingdome, the power, and the glory.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth this word (thine) imply?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It implies three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That all authority, ſufficiency and excellency is firſt in God, all is his poſſeſſion and propriety; any thing we have or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, is but what wee have of him, it is but a glimpſe and reflexion of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, it is all firſt in God, and he leaſes it out: God is the roote of all our being and wel-being.</item>
                     <item>2. As all power and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie is in him original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo all comes from him; whatſoever is in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:59096:98"/>comes from God, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re but tenants and Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ees of that they have from the Lord, who is the great poſſeſſor of heaven and earth.</item>
                     <item>3. It implyes that wee ſhould acknowledge all belonging to him, give every man his due, whoſe is this <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>power;</hi> the <hi>Lords,</hi> let him have it then, and this is to put off all ability, and ſufficiency from our ſelves, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge all to come from <hi>him:</hi> As though the ſoule ſhould ſay; Is there any thing in me Lord, it is becauſe thou giveſt it. Thou giveſt us hearts to pray, and it is <hi>thou</hi> that heareſt us when we pray.
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:59096:99"/>It is all free mercy, all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities are from thee; therefore, Lord take all the glory, for all is thine; Thus the ſoule diſclaimes it ſelfe.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For ever and ever, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That is, <hi>ever laſting pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> is in thee, which differs from all other power, all mans power is from God, but the kingdome of God, his power, and glory, is <hi>for ever and ever;</hi> We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pray <hi>alwayes,</hi> our abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities fayl, and our hearts faint, but thy power en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures <hi>for ever:</hi> the good things of this life, meate, drinke, cloth, &amp;c. ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are gone, but yet thy power endures, <hi>for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> to ſuccour us. When
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:59096:99"/>our abilities fayle, yet there is eternall power in <hi>thee</hi> to renew them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The word <hi>Amen,</hi> implyes three things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The terme of aſſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and it diſcovers the <hi>truth</hi> of a thing.</item>
                     <item>2. A wiſh, Oh (ſaith the ſoule) that it might be!</item>
                     <item>3. The voyce of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident faith. It is ſo, it is done Lord. All theſe three are implyed, but this laſt here mainely intended. Theſe things wee have prayed for, beleeving ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy will that they are verily done. As alſo there is a ſecret look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the Petition whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is put up, the ſoule pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:59096:100"/>his prayers; now ſaith the ſoule, they ſpeed; now the Lord grants my Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. As a man that ſhoots an arrow, he lookes after it; So the ſoule ſaith, Oh that the Lord would ſpeed it. So when the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions are ſent to Heaven the heart followes the blow, and lookes after them; it ſends his <hi>Amen,</hi> Oh that it might be ſo! and then faith ſaith, It is done undoubtedly, as true as the Lord is faithfull, it muſt needs be done. The word <hi>[Amen]</hi> ſtrikes the match thorow. The ſoule wiſheth, Oh that it might be done! ſaith Faith, it is done already. Prayer is as the key; when a man
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59096:100"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:59096:101"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:59096:101"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:59096:102"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="197" facs="tcp:59096:102"/>wants proviſion, he goes to the treaſury and fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it; So Prayer fetcheth comfort, peace and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; &amp;c. and <hi>Amen</hi> turnes the key. It is mine ſaith the ſoule, Prayer is as a golden Key.</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59096:103"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:59096:103"/>
                  <p>AN EXPOSITION OF THE PRINCIPLES OF <hi>RELIGION.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BY <hi>THO: HOOKER.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for R. DAWLMAN. 1645.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59096:104"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59096:104"/>
                  <head>AN EXPOSITION OF THE Principles of Religion.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="principle">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The firſt Principle,</hi> There is one God, Creator and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of all things, diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into three Perſons, Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt.</head>
                     <p>Here we muſt conſider three things:
<list>
                           <item>1. That there is a God.</item>
                           <item>2. His Works.</item>
                           <item>3. That he is diſtinct.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Queſt. <hi>WHat is the reaſon that there is a God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Becauſe in every thing there is a firſt cauſe, (that is, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niteneſſe and power) which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59096:105"/>not be attributed to any creature.</item>
                           <item>2. In regard that all things were made for <hi>man,</hi> man for an <hi>end,</hi> which end muſt needs be <hi>God.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>But can we conceive of God as he is?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, becauſe of the great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance between him and us; for when a man looketh upon the Sun, he cannot poſſibly endure it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that is ſo glorious, and his eyes ſo feeble.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How may we conceive of God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Caſt downe thy ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, confeſſing thy unfitneſſe to draw nigh him.</item>
                           <item>2. Look how he is ſet forth in his Word, as a <hi>gracious, glorious, eternall</hi> being, without any mixture of infirmity or diſability. Man hath with <hi>power,</hi> weakneſſe; with <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> cruelty; God hath not ſo.</item>
                           <item>3. Goe into the world, and view the height of its glory, and then conclude, If the <hi>Creature</hi> be thus excellent, what muſt the <hi>Creator</hi> be?</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59096:105"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A Spirit that hath <hi>life</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is a Spirit?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> It is the fineſt and ſubtileſt ſubſiſtence that can be.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Why had God rather be a</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>then a</hi> Creature?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Becauſe that is the moſt pure and excellent eſſence.</item>
                           <item>2. There is a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and us; wee have a fleſhly part, he is all ſpirituall; we borrow our being, but God hath life of himſelfe, and gives being to every thing.</item>
                           <item>3. That he is an infinite and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, the ſole Creator and Governour of all things.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is it to create?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> To make <hi>ſomething</hi> of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Wherein doe Mans works, and Gods differ?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Man muſt have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to work upon, God needeth not any thing; a word of his mouth is ſufficient.</item>
                           <item>2. Man is ſubject to be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59096:106"/>but GOD cannot.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A ſeaſonable ſuccouring and guiding of the Creature. Such is the weakneſſe of poore mortals, that as they were firſt made of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſo unleſſe God upholds them, they will ſoon reſolve to their firſt nothingneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What are the particulars of this Government?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Two: Firſt, Suſtentation, Secondly, Direction.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is Suſtentation?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The good providence of God, whereby he protects and provides for his people.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is Direction?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>H.</hi> A power of the Lord, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he orders every thing to its right end.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How doth he direct the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to its end?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. God gives them directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereby to work, and puts forth their ability into action.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What may we learn from hence?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59096:106"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Comfort to the Saints, ſeeing God is ſo great a Creator, and powerfull a Governour; there is no people under heaven (that worſhip any other God) are ſo bleſſed as they are: <hi>Among the Gods there is none like unto thee O Lord, neither are there any works like unto thy works. Pſal.</hi> 86.8.</item>
                           <item>2. This ſhould teach us to mind Gods dealing with us in every paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of our lives, and to ſtand in awe of his Majeſty.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How is God diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Into three Perſons.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by a</hi> Perſon?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A Perſon is a manner of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine being.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Why doe you ſay a</hi> being?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Deity</hi> and the <hi>Perſon</hi> is all one.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Why doe you ſay a</hi> manner?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe there be divers tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, that the God-head puts upon it ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The God-head is full of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and underſtanding: Now the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59096:107"/>Fathers <hi>underſtanding</hi> caſts it back againe upon himſelfe; for if he had underſtanding before the world; then there muſt needs be ſomewhat to be underſtood: but there was none but <hi>himſelf,</hi> therefore he caſts it back upon himſelf.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This <hi>being</hi> underſtood is the <hi>Son,</hi> the wiſdome of the Father, and the third Perſon being willed is the <hi>Spirit,</hi> who not withſtanding are all one. As long as a man tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, he is a Maſter; but when he is taught, he is a Scholar: practice comes from teaching; after a man is taught hee becomes a practicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: here now be divers behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, yet all but one man. As a Sun beame falling upon a wall, caſts back its heat; ſo doth the Spirit, proceeding from the Father and the Son.</p>
                     <p>Queſt. <hi>What is that which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the Perſons?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The God-head is common to them all; and whatever is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the God-head, is proper to all the reſt; with this difference, in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59096:107"/>regard of the particular relation that every one of them hath; the Fathers property being to <hi>beget,</hi> the Son to be <hi>begotten,</hi> and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to <hi>proceed:</hi> none of them excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the other in <hi>time,</hi> but in <hi>order</hi> onely.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="principle">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The ſecond Principle:</hi> Man wholly corrupted by <hi>Adams</hi> fall, became a ſlave of Sathan, and heire of Damnation.</head>
                     <p>Queſt. <hi>HOw muſt we conceive of</hi> Adams <hi>fall?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Look into the height of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe he once enjoyed, and the depth of miſery his ſin produced.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Were any elſe in this eſtate?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How then came all creatures to have their being?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The ſtamps of Gods Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes were no farther upon them, then to put vertues into every one.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Where may we conceive this vertue conſiſteth?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59096:108"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> In the ſoule and body of man.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How in his ſouls?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. In the <hi>underſtanding, Adam</hi> by that was full of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and capable of Gods will. Secondly, in the <hi>will</hi> conſiſting in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, God putting an aptneſſe into <hi>Adam</hi> to love him above all, and his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How is Gods Image ſeen in the</hi> affections of men?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> In regard of that ſweet Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and agreement which the <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> hath with the <hi>will.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Queſt. <hi>How is Gods Image ſeens in the parts of the body?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> When they are ſubject to the reaſonable will and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in ſuch things as God commands.</p>
                     <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the</hi> Covenant <hi>God made with</hi> Adam?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> That which was of <hi>works,</hi> was, <hi>Doe this and live;</hi> by <hi>living</hi> is meant a promiſe which God made unto <hi>Adam,</hi> that if hee kept
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59096:108"/>Gods Commandements he would preſerve him for ever.</p>
                     <p>Queſt. <hi>Had onely</hi> Adam <hi>this?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> It reacheth not to him onely, but to the good of all his poſterity.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What are the ſignes of this Covenant?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>The Tree of life,</hi> which was a ſign and ſeale whereby God aſſured <hi>Adam,</hi> as ſure as he ſaw the <hi>Tree,</hi> if he obeyed his command, he ſhould live for ever.</item>
                           <item>2. The tree of <hi>knowledge</hi> which perſwaded him, that if he obeyed God, hee ſhould certainly <hi>know good</hi> and <hi>evill.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Qu. <hi>Did</hi> Adam <hi>fall from this eſtate?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Yes, by the allurement of Satan in 3. reſpects:
<list>
                           <item>1. By pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding his temptations unto him.</item>
                           <item>2. In purſuing of him.</item>
                           <item>3. In obtaining his deſire.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How by propounding?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> He came to <hi>Eve,</hi> changing himſelfe into a <hi>Serpent;</hi> Satan be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now falne from God, grudged
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59096:109"/>the happy eſtate that <hi>Adam</hi> was in, and thought much that he ſhould not be in the ſame condition with himſelfe, whereupon he tempted him.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What was</hi> Eves <hi>anſwer?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A. Of any tree of the Garden we may cate, but not of this, leſt</hi> perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture <hi>we dye;</hi> now he took ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of this, when ſhe began to <hi>doubt</hi> of Gods providence.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How elſe did they fall?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By their owne <hi>free will</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to, and parlying with <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> in two reſpects:
<list>
                           <item>1. In a light eſteeme of Gods command.</item>
                           <item>2. In their deluſion,
<list>
                                 <item>1. Saying the fruit was <hi>good,</hi> when God ſaid the contrary:</item>
                                 <item>2. Hearkning to <hi>Satan,</hi> who told them it would be the cauſe of their good, and not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, when as God told them when they eate thereof they ſhould dye the death.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is the third cauſe of their fall?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The holy and bleſſed Law of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59096:109"/>God may after a meaſure be ſaid to have ſome influence therein.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What came to Adam after this?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> He was made guilty and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Curſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What followeth upon this guiltineſſe?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Puniſhment.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>what was that?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Originall and actuall ſinne.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is originall ſinne?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A naturall depravation of the whole man.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is actuall ſinne?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A tranſgreſſion of the Law in the leaſt particular.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Why did God puniſh them ſo ſeverely?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Becauſe they ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an extraordinary Majeſty, loving Satan more then God.</item>
                           <item>2. Becauſe they broke all the Commandements at once, which were included in theſe two, <hi>Love the Lord with all thy heart, and thy Neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Did Adam this onely to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59096:110"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, but to his poſterity.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How commeth it ſo?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> We did then what ever hee did, for we were in his loynes, it was equall with God to appoint it ſo, becauſe that if he had done well we ſhould have been ſaved; now conſequently it muſt follow, that becauſe he ſinned, we muſt alſo be puniſhed.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How did</hi> Adams <hi>ſinne become ours?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By imputation.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is imputation?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> That whereby the fault of one man is put upon another.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How came we to have origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By propagation in regard that <hi>Adam</hi> ſent his nature into us, and we become like him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="principle">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59096:110"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The third Principle.</hi> Concerning redemption by Chriſt.</head>
                     <p>Queſt. <hi>WAs our Redemption neceſſary?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Yes, becauſe God determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned an end of his <hi>Creation,</hi> now man becauſe fallen, if he ſhould be deſtroyed, the end would be fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. Secondly, God had ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the glorification of his mercy in man; now had there been no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, where would the glory of his mercy appeare? Thirdly, the Elect fallen without this could have had no comfort.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Who is this Redeemer?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Trinity, hee onely can ſubdue our enemies, and ſatisfie his Fathers wrath.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Wherefore was Chriſt the fitteſt perſon in the Trinity?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe hee could moſt prevaile with God, being his Son. Secondly, God being <hi>he</hi> who was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59096:111"/>fully offended, it was not juſtice that he ſhould pay himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why did Chriſt take the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man upon him?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe it was man that ſinned. Secondly, there muſt be a ſuffering as well as a ſatisfaction.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Did Chriſt take upon him the</hi> perſon <hi>or</hi> nature <hi>of man?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>nature</hi> onely, for elſe there ſhould have been two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which cannot be.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How did Chriſt take mans nature upon him?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt ſanctified it, and then Chriſt took the ſame.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What are thoſe things obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable in this</hi> nature?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> His union, and the manner of his conception.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How is his</hi> union?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Inſeparable, for our <hi>nature</hi> could not be ſeparated from him; the eternall Sonne of God ſo tooke the nature of man, that when it met with him, it was not changed, but remained the ſame for ever.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How was Chriſt conceived?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:59096:111"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By the Holy Ghoſt, who at this time, and in this thing imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the nature of man.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Of whom was Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why had not Chriſt a Father as well as a Mother?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Then had he been lyable to ſinne, which was principally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to man.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How did Chriſt ſuffer?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By his Death, which was two-fold, <hi>corporall</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall;</hi> corporall, whereby his body was ſeparated from his ſoule; and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, whereby hee was ſeparated from God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What things are to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the death of the ſoule?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. The wrath of God and his anger againſt a man, of which Chriſt taſted: Secondly, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences which are deſperation and continuall puniſhments, from which Chriſt was moſt free.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="principle">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59096:112"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The fourth Principle.</hi> A ſinner of an humble and contrite ſpirit apprehends Chriſt by faith, and ſo is juſtified and ſanctified.</head>
                     <p>Here are two things;
<list>
                           <item>1. A prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</item>
                           <item>2. The Benefit.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Queſt. <hi>WHat is contrition?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> When a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is brought to ſuch a ſight of ſinne, that being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to feele the burthen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hee comes to bee ſequeſtred from it.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How many things are here conſiderable?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Three:
<list>
                           <item>1. A ſinner muſt be <hi>brought</hi> to a ſight of his ſinne.</item>
                           <item>2. Hee muſt bee <hi>enforced</hi> to feele it.</item>
                           <item>3. He muſt come to be <hi>ſequeſtred</hi> from it.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why doe you ſay, Brought to a ſight of his ſinne?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe of himſelfe he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59096:112"/>will nor can ſee his ſinne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doe you meane by</hi> ſight?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A cleare and convicting ſight of ſinne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is it to have cleare ſight of ſinne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> When a man ſees ſinne as it is in its colours.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is it to ſee ſinne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victingly?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> When a ſinner is perſwaded in his conſcience that that ſinne which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> and the <hi>Word of God</hi> ſpeakes of, is his own ſinne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is meant by ſinne?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> In ſinne there are two bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the evill of it, and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Which is worſe of theſe two?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>evill</hi> of ſinne, for
<list>
                           <item>1. that which deprives a man of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt good, muſt needs be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt evill, but ſinne deprives the ſoule of God the chiefeſt good.</item>
                           <item>2. We ſee Chriſt could ſuffer pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, but not be ſinfull.</item>
                           <item>3. And God is oft the Author of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but not of ſinne.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59096:113"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is the ſecond thing in the definition?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hee is <hi>inforced to feele</hi> it, men would bee flying off from the meditation of this ſinne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How may a man feele his ſinne as he ſhould doe?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> By <hi>meditation</hi> and <hi>appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How by</hi> meditation?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. By conſidering what a GOD hee hath offended, how great mercy abuſed, and juſtice provoked, not onely in time of ignorance, but ſince wee knew him: Secondly, A ſerious medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the vile and filthy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſinne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How doth the vileneſſe of ſin appeare?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> It ſeparates us from Gods preſence, and procureth eternall miſery.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How by</hi> application?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. By convincing the heart of its loathſome conditon.</item>
                           <item>2. By dogging the heart when
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59096:113"/>there is any occaſion of ſinne, and ſtill telling it of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Can any man of himſelfe doe this?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, it muſt be Gods hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling hand.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doe you meane by</hi> ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> When a mans hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and hungring, is to get out of ſinne, though hee cannot, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with himſelfe, there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why I ſhould be thus ruled by baſe luſts.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is</hi> humiliation?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> When the heart of a poore ſinner comes to deſpaire of all hope and helpe, either in himſelfe or any creature, and is contented to bee at Gods diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How many things are to be conſidered in this definition?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hee deſpaireth of all hope in himſelfe, or in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and is content to be at Gods diſpoſing.</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59096:114"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. When doth a man come to this deſpaire?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> When he ſeeketh to the world for ſuccour, and findes none.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. When is a man content</hi> to bee at Gods diſpoſe?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> When he acknowledgeth he hath no good in himſelfe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes (if at any time God afflict him) that it is juſt with God ſo to doe, reſolving what ever trouble lyes upon him, ſtill to truſt and call upon God. <hi>Contrition</hi> and <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation</hi> are two graces which muſt be wrought in the ſoul before faith can enter in.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Becauſe every naturall man hath ſinne to be his God, now there cannot be two Gods in any mans heart.</item>
                        <item>2. Becauſe by <hi>faith</hi> we goe unto Chriſt to receive good at his hands; now one cannot goe to Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he goe out of himſelfe; before we can get the <hi>pearle,</hi> we muſt <hi>ſell all that we have;</hi> now Chriſt is the <hi>pearle;</hi> wee muſt ſell all our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions to enjoy him.</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:59096:114"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is faith?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A reſting upon God, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon knowledge, and aſſurance that God is my God in Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How many things are inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this knowledge?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A ſight of ſinne, and a ſenſe of it, which will produce three things:
<list>
                           <item>1. A prizing and ſeeking for mercy.</item>
                           <item>2. No content in any thing, till we have obtained mercy.</item>
                           <item>3. The teſtimony of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which aſſureth Gods children their ſins are pardoned.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is meant by</hi> reſting <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> It is diſcovered by two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars:
<list>
                           <item>1. Caſting our ſelves upon the Promiſe.</item>
                           <item>2. A perſwaſion that they ſhall be fulfilled to us.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is luſtification?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> When a beleeving ſinner is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted juſt in Gods ſight, through Chriſt, according to the Law.</p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:59096:115"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why ſay you accounted?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Juſtification puts nothing into us, nor findes nothing in us.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Doth God justifie wicked men as they are in themſelves?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> God provided another to be their ſurety, for whoſe ſake he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Can one mans wiſedome, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and holineſſe be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to another?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Yes, if one mans offence be imputed to another, then may one mans righteouſneſſe; but <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne was imputed to us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. therefore Chriſts Righteouſneſſe may be accounted ours. If the <hi>Law</hi> be, that the ſurety may be puniſhed for the debt as well as the debtor, then may the ſureties ſatisfaction be accounted to the debtor, both becauſe the <hi>ſurety</hi> and the <hi>debtor</hi> tooke upon them the ſame thing, and ſubjected themſelves to the ſame condition.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doe we learn out of theſe words,</hi> according to the Law?</p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:59096:115"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No man can be juſt, except he be in ſome meaſure anſwerable to the rule of juſtice.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What did the Law require?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Two things:
<list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Dying</hi> for ſinne.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Doing</hi> that wee may live.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Was our ſinne made Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> by commiſſion?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, onely by imputation, for when Chriſt dyed to ſave us, did we dye alſo? no, onely his death was imputed to us.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doth Chriſt receive from us?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Guilt and puniſhment.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doe we receive from Chriſt?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> His merits and obedience.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Doth faith it ſelfe juſtifie a man?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> We are not juſtified by faith, for its but an inſtrument whereby we lay hold upon Chriſt, and ſo are juſtified.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Muſt juſtification be joyned to ſanctification?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Yes, for juſtification goeth,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59096:116"/>
                        <hi>before,</hi> and ſanctification followes after.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Wherein lyeth the difference?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A. luſtification</hi> putteth nothing into a man, nor findeth any thing in a man: <hi>Sanctification</hi> puts a new frame of he art into us.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. But doth not God put grace into a juſtified ſinner?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Yes, but he doth it by <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification,</hi> not by <hi>juſtification.</hi> We receive juſtification all at once, and that neither admits of increaſe, or decreaſe, but holineſſe is uſually increaſed, and decreaſeth many times.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is ſanctification?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Its the reſtoring of a juſtified man into the image of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was created: Not a making new faculties in the ſoule, but put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them into right order; as when a clock falls in pieces (the wheels being not broken) the clock hath not new wheeles ſet into it, but they are new made againe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How many things be there in</hi> ſanctification?</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59096:116"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Two: Mortification <hi>and</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vification.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is mortification?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The firſt part of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereby ſinne is killed in us by the power of Chriſts death appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto us.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Can ſinne be wholly ſubdued in a man?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, but it may be leſſened and filed away.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Wherein lyes the difference between ſin in a wicked, and a godly man?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> There is the neereſt union that may be, between ſinne, and the ſoule of a wicked man: Sinne beareth greateſt rule here, and the ſoule yeelds greateſt ſubjection un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: He hath a ſecret reſolution to ſinne in ſpight of God and his Ordinances.</p>
                     <p>But in a godly man the power of ſinne is looſened, and the union broken, ſinne is not in him as a <hi>King,</hi> though it may be as a Tyrant,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Can</hi> mortification <hi>and</hi> vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication <hi>bee ſevered?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59096:117"/>
                     <p>A. No, where God beſtowes <hi>Mortification,</hi> there hee likewiſe beſtowes <hi>vivification.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Which goeth firſt?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A. Mortification,</hi> for before we can receive Chriſt, we muſt make roome for him by caſting out all wickedneſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is meant by this word</hi> vivification?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> It is that part of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereby wee are quickned to newneſſe of life by Chriſt his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection applyed unto us.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How is this wrought by Chriſts Reſurrection?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> In ſinne wee muſt conceive there is,
<list>
                           <item>1. The <hi>guilt.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. The <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. The <hi>power</hi> of it; the <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>puniſhment</hi> Chriſt by his <hi>Death</hi> removed.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. But how did he take away the</hi> power <hi>of them?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> We having ſinned, Chriſt dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and roſe again for us, whereas ſin and Satan would have kept him in ſtill if they could, but hee came out by force.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="principle">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59096:117"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The fift Principle: Faith</hi> commeth by hearing, and is ſtrengthned by the Word and Prayer.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Meanes to get and increaſe <hi>Faith.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Queſt. How may we get faith?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Word preached.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why is Faith wrought by the Word?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God hath promiſed a ſpeciall bleſſing thereunto, and the holy Spirit accompanies the ſame for this purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why by the Word preached?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the Word preached doth evidently reveale truths to the ſoule, and works more effectually upon a mans heart.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How is Faith encreaſed?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By the <hi>Word, Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>Prayer.</hi> The Word addeth fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell unto Faith, provoking a man to come to Chriſt, by ſhewing
<list>
                           <item>1. the need we have of him, by reaſon of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59096:118"/>our daily wants and infirmities:</item>
                           <item>2. The all-ſufficiency of Chriſt to ſupply us:</item>
                           <item>3. And his willingneſſe to receive all commers.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. When is</hi> Faith <hi>ſtrong?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. When it graſps as it were a whole handfull of Chriſt; a little child can graſp but a little of any thing.</item>
                           <item>2. When it holdeth firmly that it catcheth hold upon.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How doe the</hi> Sacraments <hi>ſtrengthen ſaith?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. They preſent Chriſt neerly and viſibly to the ſoule.</item>
                           <item>2. They ſhew Chriſts merits &amp; obedience, inflaming our hearts with love to him.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is Prayer?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> It is a going out of our ſelves to God, craving things anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to his will.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How a going to God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Not a bodily going, but the <hi>mind, affection,</hi> and <hi>underſtanding,</hi> ſtirting up themſelves to preſent their ſuit to him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Can a wicked man pray?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No,
<list>
                           <item>1. Becauſe true Prayer
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59096:118"/>is from the Spirit, and a ſanctified heart.</item>
                           <item>2. Theſe men oppoſe what they beg for.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How many parts be there in Prayer?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Two: <hi>Petition,</hi> which is a craving of that we want; and <hi>Thankſgiving,</hi> which is a giving God thanks for that we have.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is the pattern of Prayer?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> which Chriſt gave to his Diſciples.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Into how many parts is it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Into three:
<list>
                           <item>1. A <hi>Preface,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. Six <hi>Petitions,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. A <hi>Thanksgiving.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doe you meane by</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The firſt Perſon in the Trinity, who is the fountain from whence all we have floweth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How is God ſaid to be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. In regard of Chriſt,</item>
                           <item>2. In regard of us.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How is God the Father of Chriſt?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. By naturall generation:</item>
                           <pb n="30" facs="tcp:59096:119"/>
                           <item>2. By perſonall union.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How is God a Father in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of us?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. In regard of <hi>Creation,</hi> ſo the Angels are ſons of God:</item>
                           <item>2. In regard of <hi>Adoption,</hi> which is the taking one in ſtead of a child.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How may this word</hi> Father <hi>be a preparative to Prayer?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. If God be a Father, then he is <hi>bountifull,</hi> and we may receive what ever we aske.</item>
                           <item>2. If God be a Father, he is <hi>mercifull,</hi> ready to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all our ſins.</item>
                           <item>3. He will take in good part any ſervice done in truth of heart, though never ſo ſmall.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why doe we ſay</hi> Our <hi>Father?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A. Our</hi> betokeneth a kind of propriety and intereſt; As we ſay, This is <hi>our</hi> houſe, we have a ſpeciall intereſt therein: So here it ſheweth a ſpeciall intereſt that Gods people have in him.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Community of God to all his ſervants, as the light is common to all; none can ſay it is <hi>My Sun.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. The fellow-feelingneſſe that the godly have of one anothers mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:59096:119"/>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What preparations are there in this Word to Prayer?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> It cauſeth <hi>Reverence;</hi> A child commeth reverently to his <hi>Father,</hi> ſo muſt we.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It teacheth us <hi>confidence</hi> in God, becauſe he is <hi>our</hi> Father.</p>
                     <p>And 3. <hi>cheerfulneſſe</hi> in comming to him, as a child unto his Father.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Is God onely</hi> in heaven?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, he filleth every place.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why is God ſaid to be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. That we may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his power; things above have advantage of things below.</item>
                           <item>2. He is an holy God, for he is in heaven, where no uncleane thing is.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſcope of the firſt Petition?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> That Gods name might be honoured of all his creatures.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by</hi> name?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A. That</hi> whereby God is made knowne.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How is God made knowne to us?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:59096:120"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. By his titles and <hi>Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes,</hi> as when God is ſaid to be <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, gracious,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>2. By his <hi>Word:</hi> and</item>
                           <item>3. by his <hi>works,</hi> eſpecially in the works of grace on the hearts of his children;</item>
                        </list>
there is Gods name written as it were in great letters, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>They ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the graces of him that hath called them;</hi> ſo that when a man looketh upon a child of God, he may ſay, Surely God is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God, becauſe his children are ſo.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. When doe we honour Gods name?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> When Gods name is to us as an holy thing; when we ſee the worth of it, and manifeſt it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſcope of the ſecond Petition?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> That God may rule over all, eſpecially over his Church.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Why is it added to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe when God beareth rule, then his name is honoured.</p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:59096:120"/>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What doth this word</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>ſignifie?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> That rule which he exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth over his ſervants.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How manifold is this</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Twofold; the Kingdome of <hi>grace,</hi> and the Kingdome of <hi>glorie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How doth God rule in the Kingdome of grace?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By his Spirit in the Word he ruleth the hearts of his ſervants, and aweth the hearts of hypocrites.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How doth God rule in the Kingdome of glory?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Immediately by himſelf, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into their hearts, and filling them with his grace.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doe we meane by</hi> Thy Kingdome come?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. We deſire that God would ſend his Goſpel to ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Nations, &amp; Countryes, as have not had it:</item>
                           <item>2. That God would ſpread &amp; inlarge his Goſpel where it is:</item>
                           <item>3. That God would confirm and ſtabliſh his Goſpel, and cauſe it to have better entertainment
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59096:121"/>where it is ſpread.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is the ſcope of the third Petition?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> That all humble ſubjection may be yeelded unto God.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Why is this added unto the former?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe then Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome doth moſt of all come, when <hi>his will is done.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is</hi> Gods will?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Gods good pleaſure touching the performance or bringing to paſſe of any thing.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods ſecret will?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> That which God reſerveth to himſelfe in his own counſaile.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods revealed will?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> That which he hath made known unto us in his Word.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How muſt we be like the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in obedience?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. In <hi>readineſſe;</hi> they are they are ſaid to have wings.</item>
                           <item>2. In <hi>faithfulneſſe;</hi> they obey God in every thing: ſo muſt we.</item>
                           <item>3. Their obedience is conſtant, ſo ſhould ours. Nothing ſhould hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59096:121"/>our ſpeedy and cheerfull obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is the ſcope of the fourth Petition?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> We deſire a comfortable ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of all things concerning this life.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why is this put firſt?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A man muſt have a being, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a well-being; nature before grace.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why is</hi> bread <hi>put for all?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Becauſe this is moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for ſubſiſtence; All our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ay me at this.</item>
                           <item>2. We deſire God would give us ability to uſe the means to attain it.</item>
                           <item>3. That we may have a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table uſe thereof, with a bleſſing attending it</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doe you meane by</hi> give?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, that God would give us what we want.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, to continue and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſtill what we have.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, that God would give us an heart to make a right uſe thereof.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why doe you ſay</hi> us?</p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:59096:122"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe we muſt have a fellow-feeling of the neceſſities of <hi>others,</hi> we deſire God to give us, that we may help them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why doe you ſay</hi> our daily bread?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Wee deſire here a right and title to theſe outward things: This title is two-fold;
<list>
                           <item>1. Divine, in regard of God:</item>
                           <item>2. Politicke, in regard of men.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why do you ſay</hi> this day?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, it ſheweth that wee muſt take care for the time preſent. Secondly, wee deſire a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of theſe outward things. Thirdly, we muſt daily pray and depend upon God for our bread.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What rules may wee here learne for the ordering of our lives in the deſire of outward things?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Wee muſt goe to God for every mercy, and acknowledge we receive all from him.</item>
                           <item>2. Wee muſt onely look to the time preſent, not caring for the morrow.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſcope of the fifth Petition?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:59096:122"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A. Iuſtification,</hi> or the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by debts?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Sinnes.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Why is ſinne called a debt?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it maketh us lyable to Gods judgements.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Can God forgive our ſinnes without ſatisfaction?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, becauſe its againſt his juſtice.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How then is this a mercy that God doth forgive us our ſinnes?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Gods mercy appeares in that he followes the Law againſt our ſurety, ſo that hee is made guilty and lyable to puniſhment, and we cleared. Is it not a great mercy, that our ſinnes may bee removed from us, and Chriſts righteouſneſſe imputed unto us?</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How farre muſt a man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give another?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> In the offence we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider three things:
<list>
                           <item>1. The breach of the Law.</item>
                           <item>2. The wrong done to us.</item>
                           <item>3. The inflicting vengeance for it.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:59096:123"/>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How farre may a man forgive the ſinne as a breach of the Law?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Onely thus farre he muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that God would not lay it to their charge; ſo Chriſt prayed, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they doe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Muſt a man alwaies forgive his enemie the wrongs and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment done?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, when Gods glory and Religion is diſgraced thereby, and it may be for our brothers good.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Doth God forgive us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we forgive others?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> No, He forgives us before wee can forgive others on a right ground.
<list>
                           <item>1. Becauſe all the mercy we have, wee receive from him.</item>
                           <item>2. All wee have is but a drop in compariſon of that Ocean which is in God.</item>
                           <item>3. Our mercy is mixed with cruelty and many oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but God is all compaſſion.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſcope of the ſixth Petition?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Sanctification.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What doth</hi> temptation <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſignifie?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:59096:123"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> A proving of grace, ſo God tempted <hi>Abraham,</hi> and proved his love: Here by <hi>temptation</hi> is meant a ſolicitation to commit evill.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why not tentation of triall?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe we ought rather to pray againſt this then againſt that.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doe you meane by</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. That God would give us a fore-ſight of ſinne.</item>
                           <item>2. That God would give us pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that we be not thereby overta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</item>
                           <item>3 That God would recover us, being falne, and fortifie us againſt ſinne for time to come.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doe you meane by</hi> lead?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. That God would let us have no occaſion of evill.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, if occaſions be offered, that he would ſo aſſiſt, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that they prevaile not againſt us.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How hath God a hand in the ſinnes of men?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Whatſoever may be ſaid in the Law and Word of God, may
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59096:124"/>be ſaid of God; now the Law may be ſaid to have an hand in the ſins of men: As when counſell and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition comes, the heart ſwells immediately; as when a thing is put into a channell, or any other place, the water increaſeth hugely, not becauſe there is any water put into it, but by oppoſition.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What doe you mean by</hi> evill?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> There is no kinde of evill worſe then the evill of ſinne and puniſhment: here is ſpecially meant the <hi>evill of ſinne,</hi> and alſo <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſo farre as it may hinder us in the wayes of godlineſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why do you ſay</hi> deliver us?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Here wee deſire that God would provide meanes for others good, and make us inſtruments to deliver them.
<list>
                           <item>1 In watching over their converſation.</item>
                           <item>2 In telling them of that which is amiſſe.</item>
                           <item>3 To follow it, and never leave till wee have convinced them of it.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The right ruling over his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59096:124"/>By <hi>power</hi> is meant, an abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſufficiency to governe.</p>
                     <p>And by <hi>Glorie,</hi> is meant,
<list>
                           <item>1 The worſhip of God:</item>
                           <item>2 The ſhining of Gods glory.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Why doe you ſay</hi> Thy?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> All this is in God: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, all that men have in the world is from God, therefore they muſt render all to his glory.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is</hi> Amen?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The voyce and word of faith.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is here implyed?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Two things:
<list>
                           <item>1 An earneſt deſire of what wee beg; as a man when his friend goeth beyond ſea, faith, The Lord be with you.</item>
                           <item>2 A repoſe of our ſelves upon God, that he would grant our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, who hath promiſed, <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we aske in Chriſts Name, wee ſhall have it.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="principle">
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:59096:125"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The ſixt Principle:</hi> All men ſhall riſe with their bodies to judgement, the godly ſhall inherit the kingdome of Heaven, but repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and unbeleevers ſhall bee caſt into hell fire with the Devill and his angels.</head>
                     <p>Qu <hi>WHat are we to obſerve out of this Principle?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Two things;
<list>
                           <item>1. The judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 2. The reward of every man: In the judgement we muſt obſerve two things: Firſt, the preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this judgement, that is the reſurrection.</item>
                           <item>2. The judgement it ſelfe.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What is reſurrection?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> It is the re-uniting and knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſoule and body together, that were ſeparated by death.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Why is it neceſſary that there muſt be a reſurrection?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> There are two grounds; one is taken from the juſtice, another from the mercy of God. Wicked men they have the happineſſe of this life, and therefore they muſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59096:125"/>have miſery in the life to come, elſe God were not juſt.</p>
                     <p>Againe, the godly are here in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and they that ſhould be moſt reſpected, have the worſt enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, therefore they muſt have a happineſſe in heaven. So the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to the <hi>Heb.</hi> ſaith, <hi>God is juſt that he ſhould not forget their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of love.</hi> And the Apoſtle to the <hi>Theſſal. It is a righteous thing to render peace to you:</hi> it were unjuſt if they did not ſee ſome good dayes. <hi>Abraham</hi> tels <hi>Dives, Son, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thou in thy life time receivedſt thy pleaſure, and Lazarus paines; therefore now he is comforted, and thou art tormented.</hi> It was the ſpeech of Maſter <hi>Greenham,</hi> that <hi>wicked men have ſome good in them, therefore God gives them outward things, but they have an infinite e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, therefore they muſt periſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, Gods mercy hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed heaven to his ſervants, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there muſt be a Reſurrection; heaven is not here. There be two
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59096:126"/>ſorts of men that ſhall be judged: Firſt, thoſe that dye; Secondly, thoſe that live when Chriſt ſhall come.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How doe the godly riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By Chriſts Reſurrection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt was dead, and they are his members; Chriſt being their Surety: and whatſoever he doth, he doth it not for himſelfe, but for them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. How ſhall it be with the godly when Chriſt ſhall come?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> They ſhall be freed from all ſinne and weakneſſe of body.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Shall the ſame bodies ariſe?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Yea the ſame; God ſhall ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together all the elect: He that is able to make all things of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, is able to raiſe men, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them out of the duſt; for it is leſſer to repaire a thing of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that it is made of, then to make a thing of nothing.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>But is there no change in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſubſtance?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Onely this: The qualities &amp;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59096:126"/>conditions of the body ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, the body ſhall be <hi>incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, immortall,</hi> whereas here we are ſubject to death and diſeaſes.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, the body ſhall bee ſpirituall; that is, there ſhall be no dependance upon any outward comforts. Here we muſt uſe meat and drink for preſervation of our lives; but there ſhall be no need of them. The Sadduces told Chriſt, Such an one had <hi>ſeven brethren, and they all married one woman one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another; now ſay they, In the Reſurrection whoſe ſhall this wife be? and Chriſt ſaid to them, Ye erre not knowing the Scriptures; for in heaven they neither eate nor drinke, marrie, nor give in marriage, but are as the Angels;</hi> they need no meat nor apparel: So the godly ſhall be there.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. All imperfections and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſhall then be taken away; If a man dyes ſick, he ſhall be whole when he riſes againe; If a man be lame, or if he were born blind, or if one dyed being a child, all theſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59096:127"/>ſhall be taken away then.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Object.</hi> But it ſeemes it ſhall not be the ſame body; for if a man ſhall have every limbe, and be perfect in every part, how can theſe things ſtand together?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is nothing added to the ſubſtance of the body, but only changed and increaſed; it is in the nature of many things to increaſe, when as nothing is added unto them: As may be obſerved in an Onyon, take a great Onyon, and hang it up in the houſe, and it will grow bigger and bigger; what is the cauſe of it? not becauſe any thing is added, but becauſe it ſpeads it ſelfe further; ſo then there ſhall be no new body, but the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance enlarged and increaſed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. But how comes it to paſſe that there ſhall be a change?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By the immediate and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutuable aſſiſtance of Gods uphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ſupporting the body.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. What change ſhall there be of the ſoule?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The wicked ſhall be changed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59096:127"/>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> evil to worſe, there is ſin in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here, but there is ſome reſtraining grace, either feare or profit prevails with them now, and keeps them from ſin, but there ſhall be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining grace at all, but al ſin then. 2. There Gods wrath ſhall be pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a fuller meaſure then now.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. But the godly ſoules ſhall be freed from all ſinne and corruption that is now in them. 2. They ſhall have eternall life, and poſſeſſe God himſelfe as it were fully.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vſe.</hi> How ſhould this ſtirre us up to thirſt after the day of our reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection! here we have ſin and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe good, but there all ſinne ſhall be taken away.</p>
                     <p>It ſhould comfort Gods ſervants, though it fare ill with them in this life, yet they ſhall be freed from all afflictions and miſeries one day.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If a Chriſtians hope were in this life onely, he were of all men moſt miſerable;</hi> for who are purſued, who are hated more then they?</p>
                     <p>Now come we to ſpeake of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59096:128"/>laſt judgement, wherein obſerve;
<list>
                           <item>1. There <hi>muſt be a day of judgment.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>The perſons that muſt come to judgement.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. <hi>The manner of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>4. <hi>Who ſhall proceed therein.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. It is called the <hi>day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as the time of the Goſpell is <hi>the day of ſalvation,</hi> and the time of affliction <hi>the day of viſitation:</hi> So here the particular time God hath appointed to judge all men, is called the <hi>day of judgement;</hi> It is called alſo the <hi>laſt day,</hi> becauſe it ſhall be the laſt, and all others pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to this; It is alſo called the <hi>Generall judgement,</hi> then all ſhall be judge, even thoſe that judge others here.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Why is it neceſſary there muſt be a judgement? it ſeems there need not be a judgement, for the godly are now acquitted, and wicked men are condemned already in their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that flie in their faces; why therefore muſt there be a judgment?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> God doth it for theſe two reaſons;
<list>
                           <item>1. That his glory might he more manifeſt, even the glory
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59096:128"/>of his <hi>juſtice;</hi> for what a great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is it, which all ſhall confeſſe, even the devils and damned, that God is juſt in all his proceedings againſt them?</item>
                           <item>2. That Chriſts glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry might be made manifeſt; here he was judged, but then hee ſhall be Judge.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>When ſhall the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment come? what ſhall be the time of it?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> For the particular time no man knowes; onely we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thus much,
<list>
                           <item>1. That Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt muſt bee deſtroyed before.</item>
                           <item>2. The Jewes muſt imbrace the truth, and both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> muſt profeſſe the truth;</item>
                        </list>
after this there muſt be an univerſall decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; as Chriſt ſaith, As it was in the daies of <hi>Noah,</hi> ſo now at Chriſts comming there ſhall be a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and fearefull declining, then it will be time for God to come.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What uſe may we make of this?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> It is a ground of patience to the godly, let the wicked judge as they will, there will be another
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59096:129"/>judgement, ſaith <hi>Paul, I paſſe not to be judged of you:</hi> So we when wee are wronged and trod upon ſhould lift up our eyes and call to mind the laſt judgement, then our cauſes ſhall be heard, and we ſhall be righted.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q. Who muſt be judged?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Every man, high and low, rich or poore, all are lyable.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. God that created every man, and hath given them ſeverall ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, may juſtly call them to an account for the ſame.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. God is only wiſe, knowing how to do it, and able to bring all men to judgement; how ſhould this awe us from ſin, as God ſaith, <hi>Rejoice and take thy pleaſure, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member for all theſe things thou ſhalt come to judgement.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>But for what ſhall we be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to an account?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>for what ever is done in the fleſh:</hi> Thoſe that diſhonour God, hee will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh; and thoſe which honor him, he will recompence.</p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59096:129"/>
                     <p>Q. <hi>By what rule muſt every one be judged?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By the <hi>Law,</hi> not by the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> becauſe all men have the <hi>Law</hi> given them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.24. <hi>the Law is engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in our hearts,</hi> that wee may be without excuſe; but every one hath not heard the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> many Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and people have not heard of Chriſt, therefore they can make their plea, when God ſhal ſay, Why did you not beleeve in Chriſt and the Goſpel? Why Lord, ſay they, we never heard of Chriſt. 2. This judgement will be cleare and open. When as wicked men ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by their works, God can then ſay, Have you not done thus and thus, committed theſe and theſe ſinnes? Have I not ſeen you? As <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to his ſervant <hi>Gehaſi, Hath not my heart gone with thee?</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> God may ſay, Did not I ſee you do ſuch a thing? Then will hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites be made known; Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice will much appeare when the ungodly ſhall ſee their own wayes have ruined them.</p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:59096:130"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Object.</hi> If this be ſo, then no man ſhall have a reward of glory.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> There is a difference between <hi>juſtification</hi> and <hi>glorification,</hi> a man muſt be juſtified and ſanctified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee can performe any thing which God accepts. Now juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is by Chriſt, but glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by workes. There is a two fold obedience, <hi>Legall</hi> and <hi>Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> legally no man can obey God, (that is) in every point we cannot ſerve him ſo abſolutely and exactly as the Law requires.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>What is the difference between</hi> Legall <hi>and</hi> Evangelicall <hi>obedience?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. The Law layeth hold on a man, and bindes him to perfect and perſonall obedience.</item>
                           <item>2. If a man can obey the Law, he may merit ſalvation; had <hi>Adam</hi> but obeyed the Lord in every point, as the <hi>Law</hi> required, hee might have challenged heaven, for that ſaith, <hi>Doe,</hi> and <hi>live.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>But now the Goſpel
<list>
                           <item>1. takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the rigour of the Law;</item>
                           <item>2. It doth not require exact obedience,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59096:130"/>but ſincerity; the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor,</hi> which is taken for the deed.</item>
                           <item>3. A Chriſtian obeyeth God in his Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</item>
                           <item>4. By way of thankfulneſſe, not to merit: he that merits muſt bring ſomething in himſelfe, but we have nothing.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. This is a ground of exceeding comfort to Gods people; though their abilities be not great, yet if they are ſincere in heart, they may be comforted. It matters not how the world judgeth us, we ſtand not, nor fall to men, but to God: and therefore <hi>David</hi> being ſtandered by his malicious enemies, ſaith, <hi>Iudge we according to my righteouſneſſe;</hi> he was ſtandered as an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> yet he deſireth God that he would look upon him according to the ſincerity of his heart. This comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Hezekiah</hi> upon his death-bed, <hi>Remember,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>O Lord, how I have walked before thee with an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right heart.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. It ſerves for terrour to all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, ſeeing God will judge them according to their workes,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59096:131"/>there's no tricks to be uſed then: Here they labour to bleare the eyes of men, and to carry faire weather before them, that none can ſay black is their eye: But God ſhall unbow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell all, and ſay, This is the man who had ſuch cunning deviſes that men might not take notice of him, that had ſecret corners to commit ſinne in, &amp;c. 3. It ſhould teach us to abound in holy duties, becauſe we ſhall be judged by them; ſet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what every day upon the ſcore, not to labour for profit, but to abound in godlineſſe. It is better to abound in duty then commodity; for a man ſhall be rewarded, not for that a man ſaith, but for that which a man hath done in the fleſh; labour then to abound in piety, that ſo your reward may be great, only look you do it uprightly, conſidering God be thy Judge.</p>
                     <p>O. <hi>But it is ſaid, The Father jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth no man, but hath committed all judgement to the Sonne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> God doth put it over to Chriſt and gives him power to judge the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59096:131"/>world: As the King is ſaid to judge when others receive Authority from him to doe it.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>Why ſhall Chriſt judge all men?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> That Chriſts glory might be knowne; here he was judged, but then hee ſhall judge, which is a ground of much comfort to Gods ſervants, ſeeing Chriſt that is their Saviour ſhall be their Judge.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall Gods proceedings be?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By Books, as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rew.</hi> 20.12. <hi>I ſaw the Books opened:</hi> there are two books, the book of <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and the book of Gods <hi>Preſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> the Conſcience it is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand witneſſes, &amp; God is ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand; ſo then there are eleven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand witneſſes againſt a man: His conſcience will ſay, Are you a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, and will you do thus &amp; thus? <hi>And if our conſcience accuſe us, God is greater then our conſcience;</hi> Hee will ſet our ſins in order before us, and ſay, Look here, doe you not ſee your pride and filthines? God will write our ſins in the palms of our hands, that we may take notice of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59096:132"/>them, he will diſcover all that ever we did, to us. Now come wee to the ſentence it ſelfe.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Upon the wicked, <hi>Depart from me yee curſed into everlaſting fire with the Devill and his angels:</hi> Herein we muſt conſider 2. things,
<list>
                           <item>1. The puniſhment of loſſe.</item>
                           <item>2. The puniſhment of ſence; the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of loſſe, <hi>depart from me;</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men muſt bee baniſhed from Gods preſence.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ob.</hi> But <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139. <hi>If I go into heaven, thou art there; if I goe downe into the deep, thou art there;</hi> How then are the wicked ſeparated from God?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> They cannot depart from the preſence of his anger and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; but they neither find nor feele the work of any of Gods comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Attributes: God is mercifull, but this is nothing to them: Hee that hath not God, cannot have any reſt. Who is it that gives us reſt by our ſleep, but God in ſleep? ſo who is it that ſtrengthens us by meat, but God in meat? &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:59096:132"/>
                     <p>But now they wanting God, muſt needs be miſerable withall: They ſhall be utterly out of hope to attaine happineſſe and life; there ſhall bee ſalvation, but none for them, they have nothing to do with it, and this is the greateſt miſery of the damned in hell, that they are ſeparated from the preſence of <hi>God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. The puniſhment of <hi>ſoule,</hi> that is, they muſt be caſt into hell fire, which is ſet forth by two things:
<list>
                           <item>1. The worm ſhall never dye.</item>
                           <item>2. The fire never goeth out.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. The worme is the ſting of conſcience, that is compared to a worme, for as a worme gnaweth a man continually, ſo conſcience is continually gnawing a mans heart.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. They ſhall be caſt into hell fire, that is, they ſhall bee filled with the vengeance of God, they have here but a drop of it, as it were; if we conſider all the puniſhments that all the men of the world have had and ſuffered, they are nothing to this, but as a flea-biting in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of this: That which is the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59096:133"/>worſt, their wickedneſſe ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe daily, though they be full of Gods vengeance, yet their ſin ſhall increaſe it ſtill.</p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>But if the wicked are full of Gods vengeance, how can their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments be increaſed?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> They ſhall every day be made more capable of bearing puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: As a glaſſe, though it bee full, yet if it be made bigger, it will hold more: So, though a man bee full of miſery, yet by ſinne he ſhall be made capable to ſuffer more and more. It ſhall be eternall, there ſhall be no end of their miſery, for their puniſhment ſhall encreaaſe daily, ſo that a man ſhall be a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill incarnate, as it were.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     <pb facs="tcp:59096:133"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
